<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the Discourse of humane reason, written by Ma. Clifford, esq. being a reply to Plain dealing, with the author's epitaph and character.</title>
            <author>Warren, Albertus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18197523</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18197523</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107015</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67675)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107015)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1135:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the Discourse of humane reason, written by Ma. Clifford, esq. being a reply to Plain dealing, with the author's epitaph and character.</title>
                  <author>Warren, Albertus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Davis ...</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXX [1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: Albertus Warren.</note>
                  <note>Page 122 misnumbered as 120.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clifford, M. --  (Martin), d. 1677. --  Treatise of humane reason.</term>
               <term>Marvell, Andrew, 1621-1678. --  Plain dealing.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107015:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107015:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE DISCOURSE OF HUMANE REASON, Written by <hi>MA. CLIFFORD,</hi> Eſq; Being a REPLY to PLAIN DEALING. With the Author's <hi>Epitaph</hi> and <hi>Character.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Fruſtra ei conſilium datur, qui per ſe non ſapit,</hi> Machiavel.— <hi>Princep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Amen Corner,</hi> MDC<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107015:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107015:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>ANTHONY,</hi> EARL OF SHAFTESBURY, Baron <hi>Aſhley</hi> of <hi>Wimbourne St. Giles,</hi> and Lord <hi>Cooper</hi> of <hi>Pawlet.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Preſume to lay this my <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Peace,</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at your Feet: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, 'tis well known,
<pb facs="tcp:107015:3"/>You are a Courteous, Generous, Excellent, and Impartial Judge; and not ſo, more from your long Experience in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Concerns of your Native Countrey, than from the <hi>unequall'd choice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of your <hi>Natural parts;</hi> and beſides all theſe (which were not my leaſt Inducements) from my aſſurance of your Lordſhips Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention, in formerly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging
<pb facs="tcp:107015:3"/>the, now deceaſed, <hi>Author of the Diſcourſe about</hi> HUMANE REASON, by a particular Favour, and ſo ſignificant <hi>then,</hi> that there may be <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to doubt, whether, if it had not been <hi>ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably</hi> done, we had ever ſeen the Publication of that Iſſue of his <hi>Brain;</hi> for nothing has more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dampt the <hi>pregnancy</hi> of clear Underſtandings, than the <hi>Iron hand</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:107015:4"/>terrible <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> which was Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi>'s Caſe, till by the Mediation, and prevalent Influence of your Lordſhip, his (before) narrow Salary, as Maſter of <hi>Sutton</hi>'s <hi>Hoſpital,</hi> was inlarged; and conſequently, by this my <hi>Apology</hi> for him, I have happily gotten opportunity of preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſt <hi>Sacrifice</hi> I could, of Gratitude for him and my ſelf. If <hi>then</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:107015:4"/>what is here advanc'd, ſhall happen to pleaſe your Lordſhip; I may rationally conclude, it will not diſpleaſe the <hi>moſt Diſcerning</hi> and <hi>Virtuous part</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> ſo worthy an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it has, of whatever Action does any way ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear conſiderably good in your opinion; becauſe your Soul cannot own a <hi>mean thing,</hi> nor <hi>unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable</hi> to the Publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.
<pb facs="tcp:107015:5"/>Pray therefore, Honourable Sir, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to pardon this bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him, whoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is, and has, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, been, only to let you know, he is, and from a true ſenſe of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips, Moſt devoted, and moſt Humble Servant, <hi>Albertus Warren.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:107015:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>DEdications, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces to Books, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (if at all) uſed by the Ancients, though never ſo tempting or glorious; like the Buſhes of our Taverns, which, unleſs anſwering the Readers or the Gueſts expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, alwayes ſubject the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Scorn or Ridicule, the Book-ſellers to Repentance, and I the Vintners to Poverty: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er,
<pb facs="tcp:107015:6"/>of which Effects, no Age has been more fertile than the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern; every Apology ſuppoſing a tincture of Guilt, and good Wine not needing a Garland: Therefore all that I dare to ſay here, is, That I have adviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done my utmoſt, to juſtifie Mr. <hi>Clifford</hi>'s Licens'd Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, in his Diſcourſe of <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon,</hi> (which is the Gift of God, as well as <hi>Faith</hi>) in oppoſition to that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who, (to confeſs the truth) has as ſtrongly and ſmartly as, I think, can be done, endeavour'd to expoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur <hi>Author,</hi> not only as a bold
<pb facs="tcp:107015:6"/>and weak man, but as perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the conſequence of his Arguments, to Men, as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Subjects; which Charge, if it had been true, I, that honour Truth, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have oppos'd: but now, whether that Gentleman who wrote the Anſwer, or I, who reply, be in the wrong, (for we cannot both be in the right) others muſt judge; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is poſſible, we have divided Truth betwixt us, 'tis not very conſiderable, if the ſtanders by reap any profit by it, which was my aim, and, I hope, was his alſo. However,
<pb facs="tcp:107015:7"/>I am apt to flatter my ſelf as Victorious, from this Evidence, which no man can properly gainſay, that if <hi>Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> were not experimentally found to be the ſupreme <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in all Appeals, and the true Allay to all the ſenſible priviledges of Beaſts, then, Beaſts, for ought we know, are more happy than men: for they can think, though not ſyllogize: then, I ſay, (bate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which is our Light to judge of our Self-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by;) all Precepts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by men in Power, muſt be ſwallow'd, though contrary
<pb facs="tcp:107015:7"/>to Peace, all Exhortations to Obedience, in order to Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or Eternal Happineſs, muſt be unexaminable, and we had continued in a ſtate of War; for no other tye could have oblig'd us to keep Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, when the Violation had appear'd more profitable; and then the Laws, which Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty firſt begot, might have been truly ſaid to be, in a great meaſure, (if they who made them did not pretend <hi>Reaſon</hi>) rather traps to get money from honeſt men, than deſign'd to continue Peace: and though with me, the Publick Reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:107015:8"/>ſhall alwayes be very Sacred; yet I hope to wiſh for, or propound the Rationability, of either the Explanation, or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of ſome Laws ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and ſtrain'd by het men, and, poſibly, ignorantly zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or ill men, for their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſts, beyond, if not contrary to, the intent of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Legiſlators, in Times of other Complexions, will never be, by any true <hi>Engliſh-man,</hi> and wiſe, objected to me as Criminal: eſpecially at this time, when ſome Tools, (made when the Times requir'd them) have their Edges turn'd by
<pb facs="tcp:107015:8"/>accident againſt many quiet, though, probably miſguided, Diſſenters, to the pleaſant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring of that <hi>Claſſis</hi> of men amongſt us, whom both his Majeſty, and his Great Counſel, have declar'd, we have reaſon to ſuſpect, and prepare againſt, as our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: though, 'tis plain, that the Bigots on all ſides, and on our Diſſenters alſo, have made moderate Men, and true Lovers of their King and Countrey, uneaſie; which ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fever, next malignant, if the Reaſon of the Seat of Power cannot Remedy, we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:107015:9"/>be in great danger, leſt that Miſchief may return, which a Great Man, not long ſince, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deprecated, in words to this Effect, <hi>viz. It were ſtrange, if We ſhould be twice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by the ſame Method,</hi> which God forbid: and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Subject, by being qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et in his Station, ought to endeavour to prevent. In the mean time, 'tis better to examine, and conſult the Reaſon of things, than by truſting to any Book (not Sacred) to be ſlily Cully'd into affected, and unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Zeal,</hi> or fooliſh <hi>Atheiſm,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:107015:9"/>which will, if it increaſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, vainly project to inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate, <hi>not only the King's, but higher Evidence:</hi> nor do I know a better Method of Cure, (relating to thoſe Fears and Jealouſies, which, perhaps are now leſs terrible to ſome good men) than a cloſe retirement to <hi>Reaſon;</hi> nor better Advice for Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals, when they do go to Law, than to conſult that generally Learned and Old Serjeant, who is reported wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to have anſwered a Client lately, <hi>That he thought his Caſe was good, but could
<pb facs="tcp:107015:10"/>not be poſitive, unleſs he knew the Judge:</hi> which ſhrewd, yet ingenious Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may ſtand for a celebrated Precedent, and is as reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for us to admire, as it was for the Worthy man to give: and if it were truly aſcrib'd to that prodigious Maſter of Law, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> it clearly ſhews, <hi>'tis general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſafer for a man to truſt to his Natural Reaſon, than to be guided by Books; which are the Counters of Wiſe men, but the Money of Fools:</hi> For, though Error be
<pb facs="tcp:107015:10"/>almoſt as old as Truth, and he that in the Goſpel ask'd what <hi>Truth</hi> was, would not ſtay for an Anſwer, and that Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, after due ſearch, yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conviction, may ſeem no Crime, there is left to us poor mortals no imaginable Cure for that Evil, nor a more proper Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote for to prevent the Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of this conceited Age, than to ſtudy the excellency of <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> which will lead us to confeſs, believe and obey the Commands of the Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereof. And this great Truth is that, which, according to my capacity, I have, in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:107015:11"/>Diſcourſe, illuſtrated, not by quoting of particular Books, (tho the chiefeſt are wholly on my ſide, that way being a little out of faſhion) but by familiar and <hi>known Inſtances,</hi> and whereof, the Reader may eaſily judge, without trouble or charge: and I have declined to ſay any thing (as foreign to my Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy) in Anſwer to ſome other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Printed ſince the Anſwer, call'd <hi>Plain Dealing</hi>) about the Abuſe of <hi>Humane Reaſon;</hi> becauſe 'tis well known, the wickedneſs of man's heart has alwayes been too ready to abuſe God's chiefeſt Bleſſings unto
<pb facs="tcp:107015:11"/>wantonneſs, which does not take off from the Excellency of the Gift: on the other ſide, we are commanded to offer up to God our Reaſonable Service, and if <hi>Faith</hi> were contrary to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> no body could believe at all; nay, to ſpeak freely, tho <hi>Faith</hi> may be above it, yet few men, without ſpecial and particular <hi>Revelation,</hi> have hitherto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd the truth of <hi>Canonical Scripture,</hi> upon any other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, but <hi>Tradition</hi> &amp; <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon,</hi> which cannot be done without <hi>Reaſon.</hi> As for Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Obedience to <hi>Humane Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> which is a great part of
<pb facs="tcp:107015:12"/>man's Duty, no man (as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian) ever pretended hitherto to be warranted therein, but by conſidering of it as a general Duty, where ſuch Commands do not contradict the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: ſo that ſtill it is <hi>Reaſon</hi> which muſt ſhew him ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; and therefore, till any man can ſhew us a <hi>Safer Guide,</hi> the point is, if not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely gained, yet all preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a <hi>ſafer Guide</hi> muſt be look'd upon as very fallible.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107015:12"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY FOR Humane Reaſon.</head>
            <p>IF for no other Cauſe, yet for this, that 'tis more generous to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Dead, where the Living are concern'd in the impreſſions of Envy upon their ſilent Aſhes, than to comply with the Humours of our Dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Relations; and eſpecially, where Truth is like to ſuffer by our ſilence; I have adventur'd to publiſh this ſmall Piece, for the Juſtification of Mr. <hi>Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s Excellent Treatiſe, Entituled <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon,</hi> by way of Reply to that Gent. who wrote the Anſwer, call'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107015:13"/>
               <hi>Plain Dealing,</hi> without aſſigning any Reaſons why this was not publiſhed till now, having been written at Mr. <hi>Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s deſire, who dyed ſoon after.</p>
            <p>Purſuant therefore to my Title Page, as to the Countrey Gentleman's pretty Story of his travelling and enquiring of a luſty Follow the way to the next Town, and of his direction, (after wiſe circumſpection) to go by the Eſquire's Houſe; I am oblig'd to ſay, the Folly lay in the Enquirer, who might, with the ſame Breath, have ask'd, on which hand, or whether right on, the Houſe ſtood: but it ſeems the <hi>Queen of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> had too much influenc'd his upper Garret, being as much out of his Wits, as out of his Way.</p>
            <p>But I'le be charitable, only craving leave to infer, it is more than probable, his narrow Collegiate Education (a thing often fatal to good Wits) hath a little blown him up, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expos'd him to the Character of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantry; otherwiſe, had he conſulted, more cooly our Learned Author's very generous Deſign, and obſerv'd how ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107015:13"/>an Applauſe that which he terms a little <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> hath worthily had here at <hi>London,</hi> from the beſt Perſons, as to Underſtanding, he would have been more civil to the Writer, and more cautious in his Cenſures; unleſs it be grown a Faſhion at <hi>Cambridge</hi> to make up defects of Reaſoning with Clamour or Impertinency: if that be the Mode there, or if it be not, the Gentleman's Deſign is equally defeated; for even in the Conduct of it, he hath yielded up the Palm to our Author, as having made uſe of what way he conceived moſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to confute him.</p>
            <p>However, the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſaith, and truly, that all which the Author hath ſaid amounteth to no more than this, <hi>that every man muſt follow right Reaſon, which is his direct way;</hi> whither? to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed End; and what's that? he hath told him, to Happineſs; but he urgeth, that he who doth not before hand know wherein right Reaſon doth conſiſt (as moſt Mankind doth not) will, ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> be as much to ſeek in his way, notwithſtanding the <hi>Author</hi>'s Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107015:14"/>(which are, <hi>that a man ſhould uſe thoſe Directions with Care and Conſtancy which</hi> Reaſon <hi>affordeth</hi>) as he himſelf was, not knowing whereabouts the Eſquire's Houſe was, whereunto his wiſe Guide directed him.</p>
            <p>To all which the Anſwer is at hand, and eaſie; for if the way to Happineſs be no otherwiſe to be found out and attained, than by an orderly purſuance of Virtue, (which the <hi>Gent.</hi> will not deny) then to live virtuouſly is to live Rationally; conſequent whereunto, it appeareth, that to uſe Reaſon, is no other, than to be obedient to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> Law, of which if any man be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, in Chriſt'ndom, either he doth not follow Reaſon's guidance, or is a Fool, by reaſon of ſome Defect in his Natural Organs.</p>
            <p>The Gent. granteth, that <hi>by reaſon of the intricacies of the way to Happineſs, to chooſe the right paths, and then to guide our ſelves therein, we had need of a better Eye-ſight than is left us by the Fall of our Firſt-father;</hi> but quarrelleth that the <hi>Author,</hi> after all Conſiderations, aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107015:14"/>no other Guide than Reaſon, and pretendeth not to underſtand how that can be; nay, he putteth his Life upon it to <hi>verifie his ignorance;</hi> for he knoweth of no other Guide left unto us, after the Fall but Humane Reaſon; concluding, that the <hi>Author,</hi> by telling us <hi>we had need of a better Guide,</hi> hath confuted his whole Book: for then we have need of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Guide than Humane Reaſon, and this the <hi>Gent.</hi> calleth the coming out of Truth in ſpite of the Author's teeth.</p>
            <p>The onely Queſtion here is, what thoſe Directions are which a man's Reaſon ought to take, before, and in his Journey to Happineſs: for the Author told the <hi>Gent. Reaſon would do it, if it took right Directions,</hi> which the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſomewhat ſlily pretermitteth in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous and carping Inference; I ſay, what thoſe Directions are, and really, I (after having conſider'd the great truth of the Aſſertion) do more admire the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s blindneſs, than he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can be pleas'd with what he hath written: for, that the <hi>Author</hi> intended
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107015:15"/>by right Directions, Tradition, is obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to any indifferent Reader; which is, a due conſideration of the Hiſtory of God's Providence, his Love, Promiſes, and Performances: but, leſt the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſhould ſtill be obliged to rejoin that I alſo have left him in the dark, I make this Explanation of what I think the <hi>Author</hi> meant by the other Guide, which was, that after the Laws of Nature, the onely Rule, for ought appeareth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded by God to govern the World by, for ſome thouſands of years, at firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came either neglected, or forgotten. <hi>Moſes</hi> was commanded to publiſh the Decalogue, and ſome other Laws, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repeating the Laws of Nature, and, in part, ſuperadding, upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of all which, and of Chriſt our Saviour, we have rationally inform'd our ſelves of the Way to Happineſs.</p>
            <p>As to what the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſaith of our bruiſe in our Reaſon upon the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> that it cannot now take directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons fit for our Journey, and that it is a Suppoſition as improbable, as to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that if the Sky falleth we ſhall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107015:15"/>catch Larks, I think the <hi>Simile</hi> Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous: I am ſure it is improper, and ſhall only deſire to be reſolved by him, if Reaſon be not the moſt probable way to Happineſs, what is? But we come now, having paſs'd all his Out-guards, to his main Poſts, upon the Front whereof he boldly pretendeth to prove, that the <hi>Author</hi>'s Aſſertions are impra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable, and deſtructive to all Arts, Orders, and Corporate Societies of men; taking a Leap from the Happineſs there intended by the Author, after this Life, head and ſhoulders, into the Politick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and Concerns in this World, which, how foreign ſoever to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Deſign in that place (though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards conſidered by him) I intend to refute in every Inſtance worthy my conſideration.</p>
            <p>The firſt Inſtance the <hi>Gent.</hi> giveth is this, that if every man muſt make Uſe of no other Guide but his own Reaſon (ſuppoſe in Caſes which concern his Life and Eſtate) and muſt take Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from himſelf only, (which the <hi>Author</hi> hath not yet ſaid) the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107015:16"/>Profeſſions of Phyſick and Law would be uſeleſs; and that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Private men ſhould underſtand ſo well thoſe things as the Profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I anſwer, That the Uſe of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance hath preſerved, and ſtill doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, many in conſtant Health; that Laws are begotten and continued moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what from the Vices of men; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome are either from the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Parents, their own Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, or other accidental Cauſes, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letudinary, Reaſon teacheth men to find out proper Remedies by Phyſick, and it is only Reaſon which teacheth men the Uſe of it, or to apply to ſuch other Perſons as they ſuppoſe can eaſe their Diſtempers; which alſo inſtructeth others to apply themſelves to ſuch Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers for Advice, whoſe proper Study it is: not but that Rational men have a great deal of Law in themſelves; ſo the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons in each Science being choſen by Reaſon of man's own, or by the Advice of ſome others upon whoſe Judgment they depend, it cannot thence be ſuppoſed, that the exerciſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107015:16"/>is any way deſtructive to either of thoſe two honourable Sciences.</p>
            <p>But, ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> this alſo holdeth as to Divinity, for if men were as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of their Souls as of their Bodies and Eſtates, they would, in all difficulties of Confcience, take the Advice of Divines, as frequently as of the Judge and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Caſes proper to them; and then concludeth, we muſt not be governed by our own Reaſon (excluſively taken from all other helps) for this would deſtroy all the Chief Profeſſions of the Nation; we might pull down all our Inns of Courts and Chancery, all Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, <hi>the Charter-houſe,</hi> the Royal Society, and all Schools of Learning; and that it would deſtroy all Laws and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if every man, with the <hi>Author,</hi> were reſolved to have no other Guide than his own Reaſon, which the <hi>Author</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid.</p>
            <p>A Charge with a witneſs, but let us examine it a little: the <hi>Gent.</hi> complaineth of men's not being careful to adviſe with Divines in difficulties of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: As to the point of Conſcience, I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107015:17"/>preſume every Sober man doth or ſhould adviſe himſelf, and can finally have no other Adviſer: (yet not excluſive of others Advice, and of others Reaſon) for the <hi>Author</hi> never ſaid ſo, but on the contrary, told us of fit helps for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's Aſſiſtance, and ſurely Advice muſt be one of them. If the <hi>Gent.</hi> mean about matters of Faith, <hi>which is but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon reciify'd,</hi> the Aſſent any man giveth to any Propoſition of that kind, muſt be from Cauſes, otherwiſe he believeth he knoweth not what, nor why; who can believe ſo? Now I think there are very few men of Underſtanding but do, one time or other, conſult with others about their Scruples of Conſcience, or at leaſt, their Conſciences were not fixt to any Credentials without Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Advice, or Reading; however, I know no Law of God or Man which obligeth me to be totally govern'd in my Conſcience by any particular <hi>Claſſis</hi> of men, now in Being upon Earth: If I am ſatisfy'd, it is well with me, having uſed all Rational means to ſatisfie my ſelf; and I wiſh it were not true which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107015:17"/>the Judicious <hi>Author</hi> hath obſerved, <hi>viz. that if men had uſed their own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo many had not been miſ-led by the Errors and Deceits of others:</hi> And as to the other Point, of taking direction from a Judge, the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſpeaks without Reaſon; for he is to know, that for any Judge to ſpeak extrajudicially, is, many times, Criminal in the Judge, and uncivil in him that deſireth his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion; and for that Inference, as if the Uſe of Reaſon would diſſolve Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Bodies Politick, it is a <hi>non ſequitur;</hi> for all Rational Perſons are preſum'd to know, their Conſtitutions are founded upon Reaſon and Law; and it is for the intereſt and ſafety of the Members to obey their Superiours; becauſe their Diſobedience naturally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets Excluſion: ſo far is any thing, or all the <hi>Gent.</hi> hath objected againſt the reliance upon Reaſon, been from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it deſtructive, or prejudicial to any of thoſe Noble Profeſſions, as it appears it is the onely thing which fortifies and conſolidateth them, or all Artificial Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate Bodies whatſoever.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107015:18"/>
            <p>The next thing the <hi>Gent.</hi> objecteth, is, that the Author hath ſaid, <hi>They that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute againſt Reaſon, do it becauſe their own Reaſon perſuadeth them to that Belief,</hi> &amp;c. and this he calls, Ironically, a <hi>killing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</hi> But for the Truth of it, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to every man's Reaſon. <hi>viz.</hi> If I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute againſt any Propoſition, either I do it really, or feignedly; if feignedly, it's idle, if really, is it not, becauſe I conceive it irrational? neither can the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Inſtance help him out, which is, (and he borrowed it out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>) that though Reaſon muſt direct us to the Rule by which we are to act, yet when we have found out ſuch a Rule, as our Reaſon aſſureth us is infallible, we ought no longer to govern our ſelves by our bare Reaſon, but by our Reaſon guided by that Rule, and to act ſuch things (not that Reaſon doth direct but ſuch) as our infallible Rule doth command us; ſo that we ſee (ſaith he) that Reaſon is ſo far from being our Guide, that it directly leadeth us to the Scripture, and leaveth us to be directed by it, by which, it confeſſeth, it ſelf ought to be guided.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:107015:18"/>
            <p>It is very well, the <hi>Gent.</hi> hath confeſt that <hi>Reaſon muſt direct us to the Rule,</hi> but ſtay the Bells; Sir, when I come thither, how ſhall I underſtand to take my Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures by that Rule? that is, how ſhall I uſe it, if Reaſon do not ſtill direct me: For the Queſtion is not amongſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, whether the Scripture be true or no; but this, what the meaning is of particular Texts therein: or if any man can ſhew me any other way to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it but Reaſon, I ſhall be very thankful; if then there be no other way but the Mediation of Reaſon, Reaſon, and bare Reaſon, is to be followed: <hi>Which Demonſtrative Method, lately gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally embrac'd by the moſt Learned Divines in</hi> London <hi>and elſewhere, hath, certain I am, brought more Fixation upon men's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to Truth, than all the Canting of many years before, if I ſhould ſay many Ages, it were no Hyperbole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may ſerve for Explication of the <hi>Author,</hi> and to exempt him from the Aſperſion which the <hi>Gentleman</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoureth to caſt upon him; as if his Deſign had been to deter any man from
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107015:19"/>conforming to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> becauſe, if it be rational to comply, he that doth not, being convinc'd, it is ſo, is brutiſh; and he that doth it uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, is an Hypocrite: but if any Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter whatſoever, from the Church, have collected other things than the Book will bear, it is not the Fault of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> but the Ignorance of the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</p>
            <p>Here I might add the ineſtimable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit accruing to all rational men in thoſe vaſt Tracts of Land where the Scripture was never publiſht, and where, probably, the very Name of Chriſt is unknown, from their natural and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctive Adorations of a Deity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and conſequently to Morality, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reaſon doth invite.</p>
            <p>And I could wiſh the <hi>Gent.</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth ſo much to civil Education, and to be ſo dutiful a Son of the Church, would be a little more charitable to men of tender Conſciences, who cannot conform, without offering Violence to their Reaſons; for that, it was not long ſince, a very great Politician, and rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107015:19"/>man ſaid, <hi>There is nothing which is not made neceſſary by Divine Precept, but is eligible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> I would have the <hi>Author,</hi> when he writeth next, ſhew us more of his honeſty, though leſs of his Ingenuity: how that Confeſſion of the Authors Ingenuity doth conſiſt with the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s often future Endeavour to expoſe him to the Cenſure of Folly, though weakly enough, God knoweth, will appear afterwards in this Reply; for like the good Cow that ſpills her Milk with her Heels, he immediately repenteth of the Character, ſo giv'n to the <hi>Author,</hi> of Ingenuity, by telling of us, he is reſolved Step by Step to lead us out of thoſe Errors, which the Treatiſe of Humane Reaſon hath lead us into, by ſhewing us the way back again, by the ſame Steps we were firſt led into them.</p>
            <p>And I am reſolv'd to follow the <hi>Gent.</hi> till he looſeth himſelf, or meets with ſome <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> and there it will be fit for me in all our March, ever to retire to my Center, which is Reaſon, whoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107015:20"/>Guide if I follow, I am ſure to be very near the Road unto Happineſs, this <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I think, taking of things by the right Handle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the <hi>Author</hi> anſwering the Objection ſuppoſible, viz. <hi>That many of the greateſt Wits, by following their own Opinions, have encreaſed the Catalogue of Hereſies, thus, that thoſe men either fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed not their own Reaſon, but their Wills, or firſt hudwinckt their Reaſon by Intereſt, Prejudice or Paſſion;</hi> eſcapes the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>'s Cenſure, it is very well, how then? What ſhall we think of that frightful Word <hi>Hereſie,</hi> Which the Scripture hath not defin'd, that one Church calleth Piety, another Impiety, which muſt be in the World, and which hath occaſion'd the Effuſion of ſo much Chriſtian blood, but this, that the Tares muſt grow up with the Wheat till the time of Harveſt; and that Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath more than once, made it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that men of fiery and blind Zeal, have, for haſte, pluckt up the Wheat alſo?</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107015:20"/>
            <p>But the <hi>Gent.</hi> groweth angry with the <hi>Author,</hi> for <hi>ſaying it is no great matter for falling into Hereſies</hi> (ſo called) <hi>by the Weakneſs of their underſtandings, for they are neither hurtful to themſelves, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> and,</p>
            <p>I cannot chooſe but add Coals to his Wrath, being of the Author's Mind as underſtanding nothing elſe by the Term Hereſie, but Opinion, for how can it hurt others, what I think? Nor my ſelf, for I do nothing which I can avoid, while I think ſo, as the laſt Dictate of my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; and when I am convinc'd by Reaſon, I muſt think and believe otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Ay! But ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> is it not the beſt way for the Magiſtrate, ſince the Number of Fools exceedeth the Wiſe in Number, by Penalties to reſtrain theſe Fools within the Pale of the Church, thereby to prevent Hereſyes, Irreligion, and Atheiſm? <hi>Grotius</hi> was of another Opinion, and I believe ten parts of twelve in <hi>London</hi> are of Opinion, that to puniſh for a <hi>bare Opinion,</hi> is ſomething againſt the Hair, and abhorrent to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107015:21"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation; indeed it is not practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable now here, nor conſiſtent with Trade which is preferrible much to the Humour of a few violent men.</p>
            <p>Nor do I believe Irreligion getteth any Ground by the Peoples not conforming, nor Immorality neither; for they that do but pretend to Religion, are for the moſt part, careful (at leaſt outwardly) to appear honeſt men.</p>
            <p>Probably, it were better in ſeveral conſiderable reſpects, if the People would conform, but it will not do, nor is it, ſome think, as of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for the Peace of <hi>England,</hi> nor for any individual Mans Salvation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he doth believe himſelf oblig'd in Conſcience to conform.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Gent.</hi> is diſpleas'd highly with the <hi>Author,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>That every man's Soul hath ſo much Light in it ſelf, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for it's Travel towards Heaven, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending it to be down-right Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am perſwaded, <hi>Pelagius</hi> is not very well underſtood, but what if it be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius</hi> his Opinion? If it be Truth it is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107015:21"/>not the worſe for being his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Certainly, every man is capable to conſider God, as in the courſe of Nature, which is the way he is pleas'd to govern the World by, in the Scripture, which is the Hiſtory of the divine Providence, and his Duty, and the Conſequence of Sin: Why is it not then proper to ſay, every man hath ſo much Light in his Soul, as will lead him to Happineſs? (for I take Light, Reaſon, and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be the ſame thing) ſo that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the Text ſtandeth impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly firm.</p>
            <p>And ſeriouſly, methinks the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> trifles, in excepting at the Author, who ſaith, <hi>That we muſt ſearch for Truth in the Center of our ſelves; it being an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion worthily memorable from ſo judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where ſhould we ſearch for Truth but in our Hearts, which is the Center? and it is the Heart God requireth.</p>
            <p>Let men be of what Perſuaſion ſoever, make what Pretences ſoever of never ſo
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107015:22"/>much Chriſtianity or Morality, (which goes very far) is not Truth in the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Do not the Pretenders know, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are cordially religious, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they lay on that only as a <hi>Fucus</hi> for Intereſt ſake? But I paſs on.</p>
            <p>The next Accuſation which the <hi>Gent.</hi> bringeth againſt the Author is, that he endeavoureth to ſhift off the third Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, calling it the moſt tragical Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt him, which is, <hi>That an univerſal Liberty of particular mens Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, would beget as many Religions, as there are men, and would be inconſiſtent with the Peace of all Societies.</hi> The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Anſwer to the ſaid Objection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Negative, and proving it from the Examples of different Sects of Philoſophers; <hi>for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>There were not fewer Sects in</hi> Athens, <hi>than in</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam <hi>or</hi> London; and yet this Variety of Opinions neither begat any civil War in <hi>Greece, neither was there any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition nor high Commiſſion to prevent them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Gent.</hi> did not forget his Promiſe of leading us out of all thoſe Errours the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107015:22"/>Author (as he pretended) leads us into. I believe he would have diſproved it by a more pregnant Inſtance, than that out of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> about <hi>Apollonius Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi>'s inveighing againſt <hi>Plato</hi> (who commanded the Citizens to perſiſt in the unalterable Obedience to their Laws and againſt the not retaining in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, men of ſtrange Opinions or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; the <hi>Gentleman</hi> telling of us, <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius</hi> was ignorant of the <hi>Athenian</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, but how he could be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of them, and yet inveigh againſt them for not admitting ſuch men of ſtrange Opinions and Religion, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine, nor by what figure that Slip is to be made good.</p>
            <p>I believe there was amongſt the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> (as there is now amongſt us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, of other matters) various Diſputes touching the Souls of men, <hi>viz.</hi> whether they are praeexiſtent, traductive and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, or eternal? of the <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> about the <hi>Pythagorean Metempſycoſis,</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Daemons,</hi> the Seat of the Paſſions, the Origine and Nature of good and evil: whether the higheſt Power (God) did ſit
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107015:23"/>majeſtically idle, or did providentially govern ſublunary Affairs? whether the World were eternal or no? and many ſuch; but I never heard or read of any (beſides <hi>Diagoras</hi> and <hi>Protagoras,</hi>) who were taken notice of for abſolute Atheiſts of old, and who were therefore worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned for that irrational Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and it is very well known, what Ages paſſed away in thoſe kind of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Altercations, before ever the name of Chriſt (at leaſt before his Doctrine) was known in <hi>Greece:</hi> neither is it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to our Subject, to inſinuate, that the Crime objected againſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, was not, at firſt, for worſhipping Chriſt, but becauſe men gave <hi>Him</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honours, who was not by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Senate enrolled amongſt the reſt of their Dieties.</p>
            <p>Certain it is, where the Law is ſilent, men have Liberty, and ſo they had in <hi>Greece</hi> (at <hi>Athens</hi> and elſewhere) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, till the Gentleman doth ſhew us any poſitive Law there, forbidding Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about Divine matters (every Poet there, feigning Romances about their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107015:23"/>Gods, and yet the wiſeſt amongſt the <hi>Grecians</hi> confeſſing and believing one Supream Power) the <hi>Author's</hi> Inſtance ſtandeth firm. What Liberty <hi>Tamerlane</hi> gave, as to particular Modes of Worſhip, ſo men did acknowledge and believe in one God, is well known; and that the <hi>Turks,</hi> at this day, permit men to enjoy their general Liberty in Worſhip, ſo they do not interrupt theirs: whence a great Argument may be drawn, by ſuppoſing it to have been not the leaſt Means to ſupport the Force, Peace and Grandeur of that Empire: ſo that every Society or Kingdom in the World, doth (not to ſpeak of the <hi>Low Countries</hi>) not impoſe ſeverely merely for Opinions in religious matters, no, nor for the variety of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Worſhips, ſo men obey, as good Subjects, in all other things.</p>
            <p>But ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> Chriſtians ought not to follow ſuch Examples, if any ſuch have been or are, becauſe we have a poſitive and ſtated Religion given us by God, in a moſt clear and infallible Revelation, which our Governours ought to eſtabliſh and maintain, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107015:24"/>therefore men muſt be reſtrain'd from diſcourſing, elſe there would be as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Religions as there are men; and ſo ſaith he, the <hi>Author</hi>'s Argument remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as Tragical as ever it did. This is indeed a very Tragical Story, to ſay, <hi>Men ought not not to be reſtrain'd from diſcourſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſatisfied we have Religion well ſtated here, but for all that, we do not pretend to infallibility; wherefore, for us to impoſe, being our ſelves falli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is a little ſevere: as to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> they have ſomething more colour, they pretending to Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; though it was not becauſe of their pretence to Infallibility we left them, but 'twas principally, becauſe they ſet the <hi>Miter</hi> above the <hi>Crown:</hi> See the Laws, and the Reaſon of them: but the truth is, that Diſeaſe of, at leaſt, equalling the Miter with the Crown, doth, ſome ſuppoſe, ſtill affect all thoſe who pretend ſomething like a Title to their Commiſſion without the Law, which no wiſe Divine will do: be it how it will, there is, nevertheleſs, a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107015:24"/>great Latitude for Reaſon to diſcourſe, without offering Violence to any Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our Faith: and if I do believe any Article to be true, either from Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or from Education; yet, if another can handſomly make it appear, it is otherwiſe rational for me to believe it, I ſhall believe it upon a more ſtrong Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Gentleman's</hi> terming the Author's Aſſertion, a ſly Inſinuation, which was, <hi>That the Stoicks themſelves, who inſlaved the Will, did never offer Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> I ſuppoſe it not at all ſly, but true, and proper: for they had more Wit than to think the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding could be violently impos'd on, any other way than by Reaſon; they meaning, as we do, that the Will muſt neceſſarily follow the laſt Dictate of the Underſtanding, that is, of the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Faculty; ſo the Will is not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be compell'd.</p>
            <p>Let the Gentleman ſhew us, if he can, that the <hi>Author</hi> hath any where ſaid, the Church of <hi>England</hi> goeth about to inſlave our Underſtandings, <hi>(but a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107015:25"/>gall'd Horſe back is ſoon hurt)</hi> if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhew it, why doth he ask that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the <hi>Author,</hi> whether he doth or no? What then, hath the <hi>Author</hi> done, or written ſhamefully, to forfeit the Title of an <hi>Engliſh Gent.?</hi> to prove he hath (a ſtrange Proof) done ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing meriting that Degradation, the <hi>Gent.</hi> inſiſteth upon the Obſcurity of page the 12. and 13. of the <hi>Author's</hi> Book; an obſcure Proof, ſcarce able to ſatisfie any Jury: as if from thoſe pages, the Author ſeems to deſerve the Loſs of his Spurs, and the <hi>Gent</hi>'s. Exoration to the <hi>Author,</hi> is, that he would, upon his Reputation, diſcover whether the Church of <hi>England</hi> be there meant or no? I do not underſtand that there's any Neceſſity in point of Reputation, to accuſe a man's ſelf: let thoſe who are diſturb'd blow the Coal firſt; this is a pretty Low, not an High Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Court, but like it.</p>
            <p>Certainly, it had been more ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous (if he had not miſtaken the <hi>Handle</hi>) for the <hi>Gent.</hi> to have manifeſted to the Reader, what was juſtly exceptionable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107015:25"/>in theſe two pages; but he taketh ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Courſe, and ſeems to hold it for granted, the <hi>Author</hi> meant the Church of <hi>England:</hi> I know not how to judge of an Author's meaning, but by his words, and they muſt be theſe in the 12 page; <hi>viz. That the greateſt Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, (meaning Vexatious and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Heats) hind'ring Peace every where, have been begotten from the ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Pride of thoſe men, who (having juſtly vindicated their own Reaſon, from the Tyranny of unneceſſary Bonds) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, nevertheleſs, to impoſe upon others: ſo that, not the uſe of ſuch Liberty, but the appropriating it to our ſelves only, is the ſole Fountain of theſe Diſorders.</hi> That this is true, who is ſo blind, but may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve? and that it is applicable, eſpecially to ſuch, who ſtudy all imaginable ways to puniſh men who diſſent, and cannot comply to their ſo much extoll'd, but alterable external Worſhip, which is, at leaſt would be, very prejudicial to Trade, if the Rigour of Law did run with a fierce Current, I ſay Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce; and how one Trade dependeth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107015:26"/>upon another, I ſuppoſe the <hi>Gent.</hi> little conſiders.</p>
            <p>Now as to what the <hi>Author</hi> ſaith, <hi>That ſome Errors are the inſeparable Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of Humane Nature;</hi> a Tincture of ſelf Opinion, being in moſt men, which Reaſon ought to correct; I think it was no great Crime to ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>And to give the <hi>Gentleman</hi> his due, it was none of his leaſt Policies, ſilently to paſs by the Author's, never to be enough commended, words <hi>pag. the</hi> 14. <hi>of his Book,</hi> which are, <hi>that all the Miſeries which have follow'd the Variety of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſince the</hi> Reformation, <hi>have proceeded entirely from theſe two Miſtakes, viz. the tying of Infallibility to whatſoever we think Truth, and Damnation to whatſoever we think Errour: a moſt uncharitable Method to Judge by, I leave the Readers to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who are guilty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Gent.</hi> will never leave beating upon the old String, that the Church puniſheth none for Errour, unleſs it be accompany'd with Contumacy, and Contempt of Authority.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:107015:26"/>
            <p>He meaneth, unleſs the parties refuſe to do as ſhe would have them external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or ſhall diſcourſe any thing repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to her Doctrines; but I think, this is another Error inſeparably accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humane Nature, (if it be an Error) for who can be contented to run on in the Courſe of his Life under the Umbrage of an implicite Faith, which the <hi>Gent.</hi> labours to infuſe every where, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der other more ſpecious Pretexts: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as 'tis apparent, cool and rational men, do ſooneſt obey and conform every where.</p>
            <p>I wiſh heartily, thoſe men whom our Law intruſteth with the Power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, were more careful up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what Grounds that now contemned (but of old Solemn) Excluſion ſhould be iſſued out; for familiar Storms afright little.</p>
            <p>Next, as to what the <hi>Gent.</hi> inſerteth, that the <hi>Author</hi> might have ſpar'd his Diſcourſe about the Cauſes of ſo much bloodſhed ſince the Reformation, I wiſh it had not been true; and the <hi>Gent.</hi> muſt give me Leave, for this once, to mind
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107015:27"/>him, that while he ſo confidently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth the Church of that Crime, and all her true Sons thereof, he forgot that haughty Biſhop, which I ſuppoſe he will grant, was a legitimate Son of the Church, who, in our late civil Wars, having deſerted the Royal ſide, defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with Arms, a Caſtle againſt his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign's Forces: and it is yet freſh in Memory, how much blood was ſpilt in the Low Countries in the ſixty years War 'twixt <hi>Spain</hi> and the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and upon what Cauſe; let the <hi>Gent.</hi> conſider it, and the direful Effects of the Scottiſh Covenant, but I ſtop here. <hi>Heret late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri lethalis arando.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then, for what is preſently objected againſt the <hi>Author's</hi> peaceable Doctrine, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. <hi>viz. That to permit diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Beliefs would take away all Occaſions of Quarrels, when both he himſelf is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to enjoy his own Opinion; and his own Opinion is this, that he ought to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer others to do the ſame:</hi> This, I ſay, is perverted by the <hi>Gentleman,</hi> for the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> only ſpeaketh of Opinions, not of Practiſes diſturbing the publick Peace,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107015:27"/>for that they may be juſtly puniſhed for breaking the Peace, was never deny'd; but that the Difference in Opinion muſt neceſſarily beget Diſturbances againſt the publick Peace, is, <hi>de facto,</hi> inconſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent from many years Experience in <hi>England,</hi> of late: ſo that the Peace being unbroken, and all Obedience yielded to every Command, which is not about Conformity eccleſiaſtical, they that ſhall unſeaſonably, againſt the moſt general Inclination of the People, actually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Diſſenters in their reſpective Exerciſes of their Conſciences, are more likely to break the Peace, than the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters who keep it; and I ſay, are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd, in point of Intereſt, to keep it; that is, in Reſpect of Trade, the main thing.</p>
            <p>That the Papiſts do promote a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Toleration of all Opinions in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, I believe, nor can any man blame them, it being their Intereſt, that way, to ſhroud themſelves from the Rigor of the Laws.</p>
            <p>But for the Presbyterians, who alone (it is ſaid) are ſo fierce, that they will
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107015:28"/>abate nothing, by their good wills, of their endleſs Ambition to get power to proſecute others; I ſuppoſe their Zeal over-boyling, and really they are too blame if they do ſo.</p>
            <p>I could never think any man, very eager for External Ceremonies, which is but the ſhell of Religion, wiſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (and I bluſh to name it) far more thoſe of <hi>New England</hi> were too blame, for their barbarous Cruelty in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Diſſenters there; ſince the very Original Grant from the Crown did expreſs the Royal condeſcentions to have been for the eaſe of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences who at firſt tranſplanted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thither.</p>
            <q>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum?</q>
            <p>Nor do I think it impertinent to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert that ſingle Argument of <hi>Grotius,</hi> who I named before, to prove the irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionability of any other, as well as of Sanguinary Puniſhments, for a bare Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: I ſay that ſingle Argument, but a good one, from the Example of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107015:28"/>
               <hi>Jews</hi> permiſſion of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> not only to enjoy the liberty of their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſo contrary to what was the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion, but alſo to enjoy Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Places amongſt them.</p>
            <p>The next thing conſiderable is, the Gentleman's huffing at the Author for his Anſwer to this Objection preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by himſelf, <hi>viz. That if we guide our ſelves by our own Reaſons, we ſhall differ from our ſelves as well as others, and change our Religion as often as our Habits,</hi> unto which the Anſwer is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Text, <hi>That he cannot conceive the fear of this Scandal obligeth us to a blind, unalterable obedience to thoſe Laws and Opinions, to which either the Fate of our Birth and Education, or other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents have engaged us:</hi> and this is called obſcure and impertinent by the Gent. How the Author is guilty of <hi>both at once here</hi> I cannot imagine, for it is very confeſſedly plain, our Birth and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation do moſt times ingage us in our Religion: where's the Obſcurity? and it is accounted Scandalous to change our Religion above once, at leaſt, that is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107015:29"/>plain; and that we are not obliged to a blind, unalterable obedience about out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Forms, is alſo reaſonable to ſay for any Proteſtant, which non-obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Gent. alſo agreeth is unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>And I will admit the Gent. ſaith well, that it becometh every Separator from the Church of <hi>England</hi> to inform himſelf from his own Reaſon, and from the Reaſon of others, eſpecially from his Lawful Miniſter, (I loving to hear the word Lawful in this caſe) whether ſhe doth injoyn him any thing that is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in it ſelf; and if he cannot find her guilty of any ſuch Command, then his Separation can no wayes be excuſable either before God or Men, for it is mere Obſtinacy.</p>
            <p>But what if after all theſe Enquiries and Conſultations with others, mine own Reaſon (that is my Conſcience) does inform me, it is not lawful to obey her Commands, muſt I violate that Light? Surely the Gent. will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me to do ſo, if he doth, I ſhall and ought to deny his Rhetorick: for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107015:29"/>he is to know, it is ſinful for me to act without Faith, and if I do not believe it Lawful, and yet do it for Fear or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, it is not onely ſinful, but argues a Servile and degenerous Spirit. And though I may think there ought to be ſome viſible Judge of theſe things, that is, either the Pope, or my particular So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, or thoſe he appointeth; yet at laſt, my own Reaſon, you may call it Conſcience or Light within, will be my Judge do what I can.</p>
            <p>And now, as to the Reaſons and Cauſes which moved ſome, upon the Act of Diſtinguiſhment, to take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and yet to refuſe hearing of our Liturgy; which Refuſal the <hi>Gent.</hi> inſtanceth and calleth a great Sin; tho' it concerneth not the <hi>Author nor me</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and was drawn in by the <hi>Gent.</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Cuſtom of abounding in his own Sallyes: yet I ſhall adventure to ſay, from an unexceptionable Authority, <hi>viz. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Andrews,</hi> that <hi>de modo,</hi> of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Subſiſtence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, it was never diſputed till ſome Centuries after his Aſcention, and is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107015:30"/>not conſiderable; which ſatisfy'd a very learned King of our own, and many, the moſt authentick learned Proteſtants beſides: that, to wit, it is enough if a man, after due Preparation, take it reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentially in Obedience to Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and live, after the taking of it, like a true Chriſtian, holily and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, as aware, and minding the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Conſequences of returning to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and the great Aſſurance by hope of the Benefit, accruable from future Obedience, all which Complexion and Satisfaction to Proteſtants depended, and ſtill doth depend upon the Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of the Biſhop's Argument, where I leave it.</p>
            <p>From whence I proceed to obſerve, what an huge Crime the <hi>Gent.</hi> maketh it, in the Author, for ſaying, <hi>A man may be a Papiſt at one time, and ſeven years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Proteſtant, and yet the Faith of the Party ſo changing, may remain the ſame: for</hi> that, ſaith the <hi>Author, It is all the while actuated by the ſame Soul of Faith,</hi> which is Conſcience; preſuming, that <hi>both when he was a Papiſt, and when he
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107015:30"/>is a Proteſtant, he may truly ſay, with theſe Eyes I ſhall behold my Saviour.</hi> But I anſwer, If it be a Crime to change from Popery to Proteſtantiſm upon rational Gonviction, it wanteth a name; and that great Witt <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken who was induced ſo to change alternately (for he was firſt a Proteſtant, then a Papiſt, and laſtly a Proteſtant, and ſo died) he alledging Reaſon always to be the Cauſe of his Changes, but certainly, it was Reaſon (with its due helps) which urged him to change: <hi>that Chillingworth,</hi> who out-witted the moſt learned Romaniſts, putting them to Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, 'twas he who firſt (after Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> began and was ſtopt by Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> upon an Inſinuation that it would bring in Atheiſm, <hi>Cujus contrarium verum eſt</hi>) from rational In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences made it evident, that inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, ſcholaſtick Velitations, were too weak to hold ſagciaous men in that blind Obedience, which had long muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zl'd the greateſt part of <hi>Europe:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unleſs the <hi>Gent.</hi> be of opinion, that any Power upon Earth is entit'led from
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107015:31"/>above to ſubject us to an unalterable O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to Eccleſiaſtical Sanctions, <hi>which is to admit one univerſal, viſible Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> or if the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have all truth, though ſuperadding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unneceſſary things, and probably, impure: I ſay, if the Learned cannot agree, then it is very charitable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, men that are actuated by Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Holineſs, while on one ſide or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may be in a ſalvable Condition. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think otherwiſe, than that the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion at the laſt day ſhall not be, whether I have lived allways a Proteſtant, or allways a Papiſt? whether I have been an high Churchman, a <hi>Latitudinarian,</hi> or a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter? but whether I have lived holily, and have uſed all rational ways to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form my Underſtanding of the Truth expreſſed in Scripture and Nature? which is to purſue the main end of my Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it neceſſarily begeting a rational Adoration towards God, and Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men. Which laſt (that is, the Obſervation of the ſecond Table) is ſo indiſpenſibly neceſſary, that if there were neither God nor Devil, Heaven
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107015:31"/>nor Hell, it is moſt undenyably true, the World could not ſtand without the Obſervation thereof, and was worthily intimated by the judicious <hi>Raleigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if I ſhould ſuppoſe this Plaſter, as the <hi>Gent.</hi> calleth it, will ſerve an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then's turn, under invincible Ignorance, (as to the truth of the Scripture, which he never heard of) yet living according to the Light of Nature, I do not think it amiſs (charitably) to ſuppoſe he may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>But for that idle Queſtion of the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s to the <hi>Author, whether he thinketh an erroneous Conſcience ſhall excuſe a man from all Crimes whatſoever,</hi> it is ſcarce worth anſwering: for as much as every ſober man will grant it to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him who followeth the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Reaſon, to be adviſedly wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Conſcience being, without all doubt, an act of Reaſon or Intellect, (not a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit) it is always a Judge, yet may err, as all other Judges: but it ſits a-top, and is divine, therefore who reſiſteth it, reſiſteth his own Reaſon, and what is done againſt either, or without Faith, is Sin: what then is the beſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107015:32"/>
               <hi>Medium</hi> to rectifie my Conſcience which is erroneous? <hi>Even the ſame way that I was lead into Errour, will bring me out of it, that is,</hi> by giving my Reaſon its free Mediation without hud winking of it, darling or ſtrangling of it by implicite Faith, inſignificant Terms, violent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, and Prejudices, and Preoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, Pride, Intereſt, or other Vices, of all which peſtilent Fevers, I can aſſign no other cauſe than the <hi>Author</hi> hath done already to my hand, which is the not giving Obedience to, and not exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of that Light wherewith the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodneſs of God hath indued men as men.</p>
            <p>However, certain it is, let a man (ſuppoſe him Chriſtian) hold what Opinion he will (and we find as great Differences amongſt the Learned as the Unlearned) if he followeth his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that is, his Reaſon, he ſhall at laſt, enjoy all the poſſible Advantage that Opinion can yield him, living morally ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous: and that any Separatiſts amongſt us <hi>(in terminis)</hi> do hold any Opinion, which doth neceſſarily exclude them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107015:32"/>from Salvation, through Chriſt, is more than, I believe, the <hi>Gent.</hi> can prove: and the Diſſenters generally obeying all Laws beſides the matters of Conformity to the external way of Worſhip, publickly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and declaring it to be their Principle, (as I know, and they alſo, it is their Intereſt to obey in all other things) I preſume to ſay, it ſeemeth not, that the Magiſtrate is obliged to vex and diſturb ſo numerous a party of peaceable and conſiderable Perſons, merely to gratifie a few in reſpect of the Whole; and further to alleviate the matter, we know very well, there is a Due to God, and a Due to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to come cloſer to the Cauſes of Nonconformity of late years: it ſeemeth not the leaſt, that it is contrary to the Principles of Many, nay moſt men's Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (in the <hi>Southern</hi> parts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) all the times of the Civil Wars, other Opinions having gradually been inſtilled into them, and the Examples of their Parents and Maſters confirming their Averſion to Conformity, or theſe Miniſters or Heads of Parties, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107015:33"/>to have a Call to inſtruct them, and whom they thought they had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe, whence hath ariſen that tenacity of Prejudice againſt our Church-Government; and it being grown a Chronical Diſtemper it is harder to be cured.</p>
            <p>I may add the Act which ejected ſo many Miniſters for Non abjuration of that lawleſs, (but nevertheleſs, as they were perſuaded, obliging) Covenant, which produced Effects quite contrary to the Project of thoſe, who ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advanced it. For the People being in Love with the Plauſibility of their Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and their zealous Urgency to Strictneſs of Life, their Deteſtation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, by them call'd and believed to be idolatrous, and other cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivating Inſinuations, did really appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, upon their Paſtors Leaving of the Pulpits, all Religion went away with them: who if they had ſtay'd there, would, in all Probability, have kept them cloſer, and whom they ſince either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly followed to other Meetings, or, for want of being united as before,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107015:33"/>under ſome kind of Order, they moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd away into Indifferency, or other more wild Excurſions.</p>
            <p>And that theſe now laſt mentioned, which make up, or from whence are ſpawn'd, a very conſiderable part of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, do neceſſarily involve many others, in point of Intereſt depending upon them, to the Humour of Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, is eaſily conceivable; which hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour (if it were no more at firſt) was eaſily cultivated by more ſubtle heads, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the reverend name of Conſcience, and may gradually, poſſeſs the well-meaning part of theſe men into a real Belief, that to conform is ſinful; where they muſt be left, till otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, for Force will not do it, if Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot.</p>
            <p>I do freely confeſs, we are, at this hour, very happy in the admirable Learning and Virtues of many of our Clergy: and as for my ſelf, I do ſay, That neither the length of our Service, my Love of Variety as an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> nor being an Iſlander, nor the Vices of ſome Clergy-men, nor the Weakneſs of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107015:34"/>others, nor Lazineſs of many, nor any Exceptions that can be taken againſt our Liturgy, either as to Matter or Form, ſeem, together, Ground enough to me for to leave going to hear the publick Service at Church; which <hi>Calvin</hi> did not diſlike, who perſuaded Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi> to Conformity, and which is ſo unanſwerably defended by incomparable <hi>Hooker:</hi> but for all that, ſome of theſe Objections may ſway with others, my Superiours in point of Learning and Wit, with others of more tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, with others, in reſpect of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: all which I dare not condemn, becauſe I would not be condemned; and we muſt allow ſome Grains to Perſons, Times, Infirmities, and mens Lively-hoods, or diſſolve Commerce, the very Life and Strength of every Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick.</p>
            <p>From whence I have reaſon to hope, no Gentleman who hath taken but a curſory View of the Deſign of <hi>Fiat Lux,</hi> (which is to captivate our Reaſons to the Will of the old Gent. who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to Infallibility, and which <hi>I. O.</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:107015:34"/>as it is evident, hath diſcover'd to be a pious Cheat) but will excuſe me from a particular Replication to our Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's impertinent Compariſon betwixt the Author's Intention, and the Project of <hi>Fiat Lux:</hi> not to ſay, how much the <hi>Gentleman</hi> ſeems pleas'd with thoſe Shadows he hath raiſed, and the pretty mock Fights naturally ariſing from them.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>I. O.</hi> defend his Book himſelf, I reply to the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s next Objection and ſay, it is not ſo wonderful an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility, but that men may be thought to renownce Chriſt as ſoon by other Guides, as by following their own Reaſon, whereof the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie is abundant Teſtimony, ſettled by Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil under <hi>Conſtantius:</hi> who, ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> was wheadl'd into that Party, and that it was not a general Council, which is a piece of Confidence, only due to the <hi>Gentleman</hi> I ſuppoſe, and crave Pardon if I am miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Whether the Holy Ghoſt was ſent to <hi>Trent</hi> in a Cloak-bag from <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Covenant was in Mr. <hi>Marſhal</hi>'s Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantua
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107015:35"/>from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> I think it ſcarce worth while to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
            <p>However, ſince General Councils have erred damnably, that they may do ſo again, is probable enough: which doth evidence, that particular Reaſon is ſafer ſometimes, otherwiſe, how come thoſe Errors to be diſcover'd? And if <hi>Luther</hi> had not follow'd his own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Reformation would not have been, in all humane Probability, brought to paſs: for either it was Reaſon which ſatisfy'd him then, and others ſince, who forſook the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, or they were unreaſonable that did forſake her; and we as unreaſonable, nay more, who follow their Examples, which I hope the <hi>Gent.</hi> will not affirm.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Gent.</hi> deſignedly hath ſlipt over the <hi>Author's</hi> pertinent Queſtion, <hi>viz. what it is</hi> (for ſomething it muſt be) <hi>which is properly placed in the ſame Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Authority with Reaſon;</hi> it being evident from the very Elements of Councils, and their frequent Declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from Truth; that <hi>If God had not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107015:35"/>ſtirred up Perſons of extraordinary Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to examine, by the Rules of their own Reaſons, thoſe Follies and dangerous Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Religion, which, by the Ignorance or Intereſt of men, or the inſenſible Advances of ill Cuſtoms, were blindly embraced by the World; the Chriſtian World before this time, from the Adoration of Images, and the boundleſs Increaſe of vain and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Ceremonies, might have paſt to its vain and abominable worſhip of ſeveral Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> To which I preſume to add, or of none at all; for I know nothing hath more augmented the unreaſonable Folly of Atheiſts, than that very groſs Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which diverted the great <hi>Arabian</hi> Philoſopher from Chriſtianity: not to mention their Claim to Infallibility, and our own Perſecution of one another; who pretend not to it, yet endeavour to lock up the only way left us to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh Atheiſts, Heathens, Papiſts or any other, in the magiſterial, poſitive, and implicite Breaſts of that ſort of Men, who give the greateſt Blow to Religion it ſelf, by ſuch Precluſion of Enquiry; when the Scripture biddeth us ſearch,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107015:36"/>and we cry out upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for her impoſing implicite Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>The next thing the <hi>Gent.</hi> falleth upon (after his having abounded in his Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Rules to interpret the Scripture by) having alſo before agreed Reaſon to be uſeful in leading us to the Truth of Scripture (which Rules are ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in Books laid down) is, that the <hi>Author</hi> uſeth too great a Latitude, in ſetting the Gates of Heaven too wide open, calling it Charity with a Witneſs; inferring, as if the Author had deſigned to prove, we ought to believe <hi>Turks, Jews, Heathens</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> themſelves to be in an equal Poſſibility of Salvation with the unerring Chriſtian, which muſt be true, ſo far as it is poſſible, theſe or any of theſe are in a Poſſibility of being convinc'd of their <hi>Turkiſm, Judaiſm, Heatheniſm,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſm</hi> to Chriſtianity; and may be true, as to the Heathens, from the Plea allowable to them of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Ignorance, not ſo as to <hi>Turks,</hi> becauſe Chriſtianity is amongſt them, nor to <hi>Jews</hi> from their Obduration
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107015:36"/>againſt immediate Miracles done for their Converſion, nor to Atheiſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are convincible from the courſe of all natural Agents, though the Author only ask'd the Queſtion, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ought to believe theſe be forenamed were in an equal poſſibility of Salvation with Chriſtians?</hi> and to ſhew he did not believe it, he confeſſeth, <hi>there is no other name to be ſaved by</hi> (that is, to ſpeak ſtrictly) <hi>but that of Chriſt,</hi> and then ſubjoyneth, that he may very well believe, there are other ſecret and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ways, by which God may be pleas'd to apply his Merits (that is, Chriſt's Merits to mankind) beſides thoſe direct, open, and ordinary ones of Baptiſm and Confeſſion; which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is no Crime to ſay, nor hard to prove, if the time would give Leave; ſo that for all theſe Scratches of the <hi>Gent.</hi> the Author's Charity is ſafe enough. Let us ſee how charitable the <hi>Gent.</hi> is to his own Countrymen; for I muſt make Leaps as he doth, elſe I cannot overtake him.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:107015:37"/>
            <p>To evidence it, <hi>pag.</hi> 75. of his Anſwer, he ſaith, that when he ſeeth others, when they ſhould worſhip God, ſit on their Tails like <hi>Dogs, or wallow and loll, and grunt, and groan like Swine, or ſtand up and wriggle and make ugly Faces, and grin and make Mouths like Apes, or Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boons,</hi> he muſt confeſs, he cannot, for his Soul, but think, their way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ridiculous and contrary to the due Expreſſions of the Reverence they owe to the infinite God of Heaven and Earth, which is the Witneſs of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Now pray obſerve if I have not Reaſon enough to think, that the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi>'s way of Worſhip may ſeem as ridiculous to the others; I am ſure his Cenſure is very uncharitable: for though men, worſhipping according to their Conſciences, may miſs, in legal Circumſtance, yet it is rational to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, there's much of Devotion in their manner of worſhip: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was of another mind than this Gent. is, for he would not eat, <hi>rather than offend his weak Brother;</hi> and there is no one thing more preſs'd by Chriſt, than Charity,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107015:37"/>which I leave to the <hi>Gent</hi>'s. Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at his Leiſure.</p>
            <p>But he objecteth againſt the <hi>Author,</hi> for ſaying, <hi>That as well different Thoughts may repreſent the Worſhip of God and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, as different Words can repreſent the ſame Thoughts;</hi> which the <hi>Gent.</hi> termeth an extravagant Aſſertion in the literal Senſe of it; to which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>It is poſſible I may have Thoughts of God's ſeveral Repreſentation of himſelf, as by <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the <hi>Man Chriſt,</hi> by his Apoſtles, which is to worſhip him for his gradual Exertion of himſelf; and in the Wiſdom and Method of his Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and otherwiſe; I may reflect upon the Creation of the World beyond that, upon the firſt Race of Intellectuals: and then again, of the fall of man, his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby ſubjected to God's Wrath; and finally of Chriſt's Paſſion; which put us again into a potentiality of being ſaved: by all which (to inſtance in no more) I do render him no different, but one Worſhip, though every part of my Worſhip be not at all times ſubtiliz'd
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107015:38"/>in my Imagination and Memory. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though I ſhould admit to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman,</hi> that the Worſhip of God is eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially plac'd in the Thoughts, it doth not thence follow, as he would have it (though illogically) that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Thoughts muſt make different Worſhips; for there is allways an Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Worſhip both natural, and grounded upon revealed Truths: and if internal Worſhip be no more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of all ways, according to the beſt of my Reaſon (ſo govern'd) to honour God, by, from and under the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to me, of his incomprehenſible Exiſtence and Power, I ſhall have much Peace by it.</p>
            <p>Again, How diſingeniouſly the <hi>Gent.</hi> endeavoureth to poſſeſs his Readers, that the <hi>Author</hi> goeth about to prove a man may be excuſable, though he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth humane Reaſon, to the denyal of Chriſtianity; when the <hi>Author</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 57. <hi>and</hi> 58. <hi>That the beſt and trueſt humane Reaſon could not have found out, of it ſelf, the Wiſdom of God in a Myſtery, ev'n that hidden Wiſdom
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107015:38"/>which God ordain'd before the World, which is the Myſtery of Chriſt, Jeſus Chriſt; for ſaith the</hi> Author, <hi>it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it ſhould be firſt revealed by the Spirit of God, which can only diſcover the deep things of God, but as ſoon as God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed it by Miracles, fulfilling of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, humane Reaſon was able to behold it, and confeſs it, not that Grace had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the Eye-ſight of humane Reaſon, but that it had drawn the Object nearer to it.</hi> So far is the Learned Author from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that a man may be excuſable by following of Reaſon to the Denyal of Chriſtianity, that he hath made it primarily ſubſervient to the Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and yet capable to embrace the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionability of Scripture-evidence; which is one of the main, but not the ſole Foundations of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>And for Anſwer to the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s confident Challenge to the <hi>Author,</hi> that he would prove, that ever the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Greeks</hi> had amongſt them any Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion which they defended, more direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to the Chriſtian Religion, than the Author's, I ſuppoſe he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:107015:39"/>our Relyance upon Reaſon. I will Inſtance in one only, though I might produce more, and that is, the <hi>Epicure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> Doctrine, which acknowleding God, deny'd nevertheleſs his Providence, by pretending it below and inconſiſtent with his Majeſty Divine, to trouble it ſelf with humane Affairs: but if Providence had been exploded out of the minds of men, it had been impoſſible to have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded us, that God was ever diſpleas'd at the Fall of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an;</hi> and conſequently, there would have appear'd no need at all of Reſtauration by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Gent.</hi> flyeth yet higher in the very ſame page, by charging the <hi>Author</hi> that he hath buſied himſelf to prove, Humane Reaſon may, with Safety to eternal Happineſs, tolerate Atheiſm it ſelf, and conſequently, all kind of Luſts and Wickedneſs whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Really, a moſt irrational and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Objection; ſuch an Objection, as no man, who pretendeth to be a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but would bluſh to make: to cancel which, I need do no more than repeat the Author's own Words. <hi>pag.</hi> 31.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107015:39"/>which are theſe, <hi>I believe firſt, that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelf will declare to every man in the World, that he ought to adhere to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, rather than to any other, Religion in the World.</hi> Now if Chriſtian Religion ought to be adhered to, it followeth neceſſarily, that Vertue ought to be embrac'd, and Vice deteſted, becauſe that Religion doth engage men to Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without the Practiſe whereof, none can be happy, according to the very Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Religion.</p>
            <p>The next things quarrell'd at, are thoſe Poſitive and undeniable Arguments which the Author propoundeth to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, the Excellency of Humane Reaſon, (taking it with it's due Helps) that is, by comparing it with other Guides, ſtanding in Competition with it: in the Proſecution whereof, how learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, accurately, and judiciouſly, the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> hath particularly demonſtrated the Uncertainty of many other pretended Guides, and the Improbability of their being able to ſatisfie a ſolid Inquiſition after Truth, and which we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to make, and for which, the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107015:40"/>
               <hi>Bereans</hi> were called noble, appeareth ſo clearly from the 62 <hi>pag.</hi> of his book to <hi>pag.</hi> 64. that I dare ſay, no unprejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Reader having conſidered them, will ſuppoſe leſs than this, that his Arguments need not any other Proof, but the bare Prolation.</p>
            <p>But however, to give the <hi>Gent.</hi> fair Play, I will go back a little to the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's page</hi> 63. where he proveth Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity leſs ſafe than humane Reaſon; out of which the <hi>Gent.</hi> would very fain ſqueeze ſomething like a Face of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction; to which I anſwer.</p>
            <p>He that believeth any thing becauſe enjoyned by Authority, is not, nor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in his own Conſcience, be ſo faſe, as he that believeth and obeyeth Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; becauſe he is rationally convinc'd he ought to obey it, having commanded a rational thing.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Inſtance of the Judges paſſing Sentence <hi>Secundum alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata &amp; probata,</hi> he is miſtaken; for our Judges do not ſo judge, nor will our municipal Law bear it (nor is it any thing pertinent to the Buſineſs in hand)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:107015:40"/>for it is the Jury that groundeth the Sentence here, the Judge only pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it.</p>
            <p>And touching the <hi>Gentleman's</hi> Inſtance about <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, from want of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the Dictates of his own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, aſſerted by the Author, and which the <hi>Gent.</hi> would elude, by ſaying that <hi>Adam</hi>'s Crime was for believing <hi>Eve,</hi> rather than his own Reaſon; inſiſting, that the Inhibition was not a Law of Nature or Reaſon, but a mere poſitive Law. I anſwer, if the Law were mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſitive, <hi>Adam</hi> had the greater Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to obſerve it, and therefore it was irrationally done, to follow the Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his Wife (you may call it Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority if you pleaſe, conſidering our Wives now in <hi>England</hi>) before the Command of his Maker, and indeed a thing altogether unbecoming his maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Superiority; and by the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Favour, <hi>Eve</hi> did not plead the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but Fraud of the Serpent which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled her, nor did the Serpent pretend to any Dominion over her.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107015:41"/>But I ſee the <hi>Gent.</hi> groweth angry, by his Excurſions in the upper part of his 96. <hi>pag.</hi> being nothing civil at all to the Author, nor indeed pertinent to the Controverſie: which for the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s own ſake, becauſe poſſibly, 'twas but the effect of mere Paſſion, I ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to mention here particularly, and now I muſt look backwards.</p>
            <p>To what is objected againſt the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s Words, which are, <hi>That they who commit themſelves to the Guidance of their own Reaſon, if they do commit themſelves wholly to it, are as ſafe on the Left band, as on the Right: as ſecure of Happineſs in their Errors, as others are who are otherwiſe guided ev'n in the Truths which they happ'n to fall into.</hi> I ſuppoſe it is no more than if he had ſaid, that Councils, Doctors, Fathers, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Churches <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have erred both ways: and therefore I am in as great Danger in ſubmitting to ſuch fallible and blind Guides every whit, nay great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, than if I happ'n to err, after having ſearcht, with all the imaginable Strength of my Reaſon, for Truth: for ſaith the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107015:41"/>
               <hi>Author, There is no danger of periſhing but for Diſobedience,</hi> to what? <hi>to God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands:</hi> and I am commanded to offer a reaſonable Service, <hi>I am to give a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my Faith, and that Hope which is in me,</hi> and doth it look like a good Plea to ſay, that I did ſearch, and pray'd to God, to direct me in that Search by his Spirit? or is it better to ſay, and more tolerable, that I believ'd as the Church believ'd, and reſted there as ſafe I thought, as a Thief in a Mill? but this laſt Plea can never hold, for me to pretend I did ſo with other men's Eyes, when God hath giv'n me Eyes of mine own: and this made <hi>Luther</hi> ſtir, and <hi>H.</hi> 8. too; who being King of a Kingdom independent of <hi>Rome,</hi> properly (though many ways uſurpt by the Pope) was not, <hi>à parte rei,</hi> obliged to refer himſelf to the Deciſion of any foreign Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate about that which, he alledg'd, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bl'd his Conſcience; or if it were from any other Motive, yet it was generouſly done upon the main; and God can bring Good out of Evil: whence the <hi>Author</hi>'s Aſſumption, <hi>that there is in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107015:42"/>man a natural Ability of ſearching for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Truths, and that it can be nothing elſe but the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> neither to any thing elſe can the Command of ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be directed <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot be ſhaken by what is objected; beſides that, the Author has the Suffrage of the beſt learned in all Ages to back him.</p>
            <p>As to what fell in betwixt the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> and Maſter <hi>Hobbs,</hi> it doth not much concern me to meddle with, in this place, <hi>T. H.</hi> will ſhift for himſelf: but I will tell the <hi>Gent.</hi> he is the firſt Chriſtian that ever interpreted the fifth of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Let your Light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works,</hi> to warrant the Neceſſity of Obedience to external Worſhip; nor will the Scope of that Chapter bear it, the Apoſtle intending to explain thereby, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed State of Chriſtianity in Suffering for Chriſt. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that it is impoſſible, Humane Reaſon (ſo guided as the <hi>Author</hi> hath told us) ſhould lead men into thoſe Sins of Theft, Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all other Villanies, appeareth from this, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107015:42"/>elſe beſides it, can preſerve us from the Commiſſion of them; for no man while he uſed his own Reaſon rightly, ever committed any of them, it being impoſſible to ſuppoſe it could be the Effect of Reaſon, to be impious, but it may be the effect of the enſlaving of our Reaſon, to the brutiſh part of a man, which is his ſenſual Appetite, or the like, which indeed is too familiar while Youth laſteth.</p>
            <p>It is true which the <hi>Gent.</hi> affirmeth, that whoever faileth by the willfull ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of finding out of Truth, which was in his Power to help, is therefore inexcuſable; but he that perſecutes thoſe who have ſearcht according to their beſt means, and yet cannot ſatisfie their own Conſciences, is more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable; by doing that to others which he would (for no man would be perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted) not have done to himſelf.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Gentleman</hi> excepts againſt the Author's aſſerting, <hi>That we ought not to believe Errors of Faith to be damnable, it being unreaſonable to teach men, that Errors overthrow our Hopes of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107015:43"/>Salvation, unleſs we could likewiſe give them a Catalogue of thoſe Errors which are ſo: Paul</hi> indeed ſaith, there are damnable Hereſies, and <hi>Peter,</hi> but names none in particular, <hi>but denying of the Lord that bought us, thereby bringing ſwift Deſtruction, &amp;c.</hi> it is very plain thereby, <hi>Peter</hi> defin'd, or rather determin'd the denying of the Lord that bought them, to be the only damnable Hereſie, which indeed I take to be Apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>However the <hi>Gent.</hi> adventureth to give us another manner of Catalogue of damnable Hereſies, which he ſaith, are all ſuch as are continued in, in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Authority of the Church perverſely and obſtinately; I grant it true. But if all are guilty of damnable Errors, or damnable Hereſie, who do not obey what the Church enjoyneth, that is, the Law in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> conſidering the Indifferency of ſome, and the diſſenting of others; there will be but a few compar'd to the guilty, in any Poſſibility of Salvation in thoſe two Kingdoms; and it muſt needs invite all lukewarm Proteſtants
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:107015:43"/>to the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, rather than to ſtick to the Religion of that people, ſo generally infected with damnable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; the Papiſts have reaſon to thank him for it.</p>
            <p>Yet again, the <hi>Gent.</hi> quarrelleth at the <hi>Author,</hi> for ſaying; <hi>Where we do not know our Fault, we have no means of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting of it, and conſequently, cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Pardon for it, there being no Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs without Repentance, and Repentance is impoſſible without knowledge of our Fault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s anſwer is, if this be true, it would damn all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; and my Reply is, <hi>If it be not true, it muſt damn moſt of Mankind:</hi> for confident I am, there's not one in a thouſand that thinketh himſelf obliged to repent of Sins he never knew of, it being enough, and more than moſt men do, to repent of known ſins. Pardon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth a Guilt, Guilt is a Breach of the Law. The old Teſtament condemneth none but for actual Sins, the new ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth few new Sins, more than the old: for Thoughts, if tranſient, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107015:44"/>into Act, are not Sins; and what <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Who can underſtand his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors?</hi> there is not any more meant by it, than that it is difficult to underſtand them; and when he prayeth to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd his ſecret Sins, he intended not any other than ſuch Sins, as were only known to God and himſelf; ſo againſt preſumptuous Sins, which are intended againſt Light, againſt Reaſon, no man having ever had greater Reaſon to be thankful to God than he, who had been preferr'd and preſerved in ſo admirable a manner, more than once from his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>Gent.</hi> cannot forget who prayed to be deliver'd from unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable men, nor who fought with Beaſts at <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the <hi>Author</hi> having ſaid, the great Probability of Truth on all ſides, ev'n in the erring ones, ought to make us believe, that God will pardon thoſe Errors: the <hi>Gentleman</hi> anſwers thus.</p>
            <p>If our Errors be ſuch as are not the Effects or Cauſes of any Sin, we have no Reaſon to think but God will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them: and I ſay, <hi>If our Sins be the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107015:44"/>Cauſes of our Errors, we have no Reaſon to think, that God will pardon them;</hi> and that Sin is for the moſt part the Cauſe of Errors, is plain to any man who ſhall obſerve the Effects of Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery: for how is it poſſible, any man can act rationally, who drowneth his Reaſon? or believe, as convinc'd by Reaſon, when he will offer Violence to it, and brutifie himſelf.</p>
            <p>But ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> if our Errors are the Effect of willfull Ignorance, Pride or Idleneſs, if they have lead us into Schiſm and Hereſie, and thereby into Contempt of Authority, then we can have no Hopes of Pardon without Amendment; wherefore Sin being moſt commonly the Cauſe or the Effect of Errors, or both, it proveth there is no ſmall Danger in them.</p>
            <p>I muſt mind the Reader here, how the <hi>Gentleman</hi> runneth the <hi>Wild-gooſe Chaſe;</hi> one while putting an erroneous perſon in hope of Pardon (in which he implieth Guilt) or elſe why Pardon? Another while, no Pardon without Amendment; as if Amendment were
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:107015:45"/>not the tacite Condition of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; which if it were not true, men might preſume to ſin daily upon Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of daily Pardon, or, at leaſt, upon Preſumption of it: I ſuppoſe he ſhould rather have ſaid, no Pardon was to be had without Repentance in any Caſe: which he was afraid, or unwilling to ſay, leaſt he ſhould have admitted the Truth of the <hi>Author's</hi> Aſſertion, which was, that true Repentance could not be without fore-knowledge of the Fault; and I think, as concerning Errors, to mend is no more than to repent of them.</p>
            <p>But for that the Gent. makes Wilful Ignorance a damnable ſin, I do not well underſtand what he meaneth by the term <hi>Wilful,</hi> there, it being as abſurd, to my apprehenſion, to call Ignorance, <hi>Wilful,</hi> as to talk of <hi>Free Will;</hi> the Will alwayes following, and being acted by the laſt Dictate of the Underſtanding: ſo that, it not only ſeemeth to be, but is neceſſitated, being no Faculty in it ſelf: men cannot therefore believe what they pleaſe, nor think what they pleaſe,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:107015:45"/>that ſuch or ſuch an Opinion, or thing, is true or falſe. Indeed a man may act contrary to his Underſtanding, which is Hypocriſie, and which, if the Gent. pleaſeth, he may call Wilful Hypocriſie: nor do I know a fitter man to make Hypocrites than himſelf, who is ſo fierce, nay fiercer than our Laws are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to have all men compelled to Conformity, whether it be with or againſt their Reaſons, after the way Carters uſe, by the Whip, to teach their poor Horſes obedience.</p>
            <p>Now again; the <hi>Author</hi> having ſaid, and truly, <hi>that there is no ſuch great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from Errors, ſince there is but one true way for a thouſand falſe ones, and that there's no mark ſet upon that true way, to diſtinguiſh it from others,</hi> (Reaſon being the Judge) the <hi>Gent.</hi> argueth, that where the difficulty ſurpaſſeth the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that God hath given us <hi>(Reaſon ſtill, for we have no other)</hi> we need not fear he will puniſh us for not finding out ſuch Truths: (Where's Wilful Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance now? for, ſaith he, if they had been neceſſary (I wiſh he had told us
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:107015:46"/>what are neceſſary for our Salvation,) they would have been ſuited to our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, but if we are wilfully ignorant of neceſſary Truths, then it is not more contrary to the Goodneſs of God to puniſh us Eternally for that, than for any other ſin which we dye in, without Repentance. I reply,</p>
            <p>That in all Caſes where I cannot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any Propoſition about Faith, (becauſe unconvinc'd) having ſearch'd and try'd what poſſibly I could to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince or inform my ſelf; I need not fear God will puniſh me eternally; for, in this caſe, I cannot be guilty of that he calleth Wilful Ignorance, for it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that all Truths which I aſſent not to (having ſo ſearch'd by my Reaſon) do either ſurpaſs my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or they do not: if they do, I am not puniſhable, ſaith the <hi>Gent.</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, and I ſay, <hi>If they do I am not puniſhable eternally, becauſe I could not know they were Truths; Puniſhment al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes preſuppoſing Guilt, and it is no Crime not to be able to know, but a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Infirmity: indeed it is a Crime not to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107015:46"/>ſearch for Truth; but none to think ſuch a Poſition falſe; Neither do I know that men are any were, in Scripture ſaid to be condemned eternally for any other but unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented actual Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if I ſhould grant that ſome Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors are damnable, how ſhall I know which are ſo? one Church condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another, muſt not my Reaſon judge for me?</p>
            <p>Yet higher, If it be hard to ſay, which a Great Author ſaith, not yet anſwer'd, (nor perhaps ever will) <hi>that God who is the Father of Mercies, that doeth, in Heaven and Earth, all that he will, that hath the Hearts of all men in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, that Worketh in men both to Will and to Do, and without whoſe free gift a man hath neither inclination to Good, nor repentance of Evil, ſhould puniſh mens Tranſgreſſions without any end of Time, and with all the extremity of Torture that men can imagine, and more:</hi> it ſeemeth hard to think (which I add) that he will puniſh men eternally for not being able to find out the Truth: harder for their Errors, which they believe to be Truth,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107015:47"/>but hardeſt of all, for not conforming to the External Modes of honouring him, which are alterable, and many times accommodated to the Intereſt of a Nation; and are only honourable to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, becauſe they are legally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to be honourable in one place, not ſo in another. How much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth it concern the Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, every where, to conſider and weigh the preſent <hi>Genius</hi> of the People, before they make Eccleſiaſtical Laws? for they alwayes touch the Conſciences of men, not ſo other Laws (for they are for Publick Peace (ſtrictly) and muſt be obey'd) they are, I ſay, to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, eſpecially there, where, in the very Nature of the People, there is much pity for Sufferers about Religious concerns, and in whom there is a general abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (as with us, about Religion) from Perſecution, which His Majeſty well underſtood, when he afforded that Gracious Condeſcention: beſides, all men know, Perſuaſion was the Method of the Apoſtles, not Rigor, nor will Rigor prevail here.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:107015:47"/>
            <p>And we have lived to ſee (once more to ſay it) the Profit of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative and rational way of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Printing uſed of late; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. D. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Book Entitled <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Sacrae,</hi> that moſt Excellent Book, proving the Being of God, the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the Soul, and the truth of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, is no mean Example; nor are D. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Printed Sermons leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable againſt Atheiſm. From whence I paſs by (as granted on all hands) the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s long Harangue (which he before play'd with) of the Rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of Men's being obliged to conſult with Divines, Lawyers and Phyſicians, as anſwered before.</p>
            <p>Though I may pertinently ſubjoyn, what great Reaſon our <hi>Author</hi> had to mention the Ignorance or Malice of one ſort of our ſpiritual Phiſicians, together with their too viſible Vices (I mean in ſome of them) as none more likely to let in a Flood of Atheiſm and Popery, than the Diſobedience of Diſſenters: from whence I paſs to the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s next Argument againſt our Relyance upon
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:107015:48"/>Reaſon; he putting the caſe, <hi>of meeting with a Jeſuit, or Sectary, who ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque me, how I will avoid being made ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe two?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I muſt reply, and can give no other than this, that in ſuch a Caſe, I muſt fly to Reaſon as my ſafeſt Guard; all other Guides being fallible, which no man in his Wits was ever yet ſo ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational as to ſay of Reaſon, nor the <hi>Gentleman neither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet to ſpeak freely, I cannot think otherwiſe, but that I am obliged to yield to either of thoſe two, if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear either of them to have greater Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than mine; and that I may be ſafe with either of them, the <hi>Gent.</hi> allows: ſo there's no Danger at all, in meeting with either the one or the other, but a poſſible Profit.</p>
            <p>So great is the uſe of Reaſon, and ſo great is the Force and Defence of it. The plain Truth is, it is the thinking man that is wiſe. As for Books, they may be uſeful, yet 'tis dangerous rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon them: 'tis true, a few Books well choſen and digeſted may open and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:107015:48"/>eſtabliſh the Underſtanding, when as too much reading dazles it: how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Perſons of good Natural Parts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Wit and Learning, wear out their dayes in a perpetual hurry of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is obvious to every man of general Converſation; <hi>ſuch are alwayes learning, and never come at truth.</hi> So that every Humane Excellency reſolves into Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or ſhrowds under its Umbrage; Reaſon, which (as a Light Divine) govern'd the World before the Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical word <hi>Conſcience</hi> was known.</p>
            <p>This begot Government, teaches O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; and, firſt of all, oblig'd men to Natural Religion, which can never be cancell'd or forgotten. All the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers in the World cannot make any Caſe Law, which is not Reaſonable; 'tis not Precedents will do it, they are but Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. Nor can any Divine preach me into a belief of any Propoſition, unleſs he be able to convince my Reaſon, that what he ſayes is true. Nor any Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian warrant the ſoundneſs of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to his Sovereign, till the Event has juſtified the Rationability of his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:107015:49"/>Counſel, which is the Reaſon, why it has been obſerved, that ſome wary men in Counſels endeavour to ſpeak laſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis hard to conceive, what that thing is, which the Learned call <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Fatum;</hi> ſo many little (and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be foreſeen) intervening Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, may, and do often, alter the moſt ſubtile Projections.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, a Rational and Prudent man may live in Peace in moſt Times, under the changes of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by complying; as Judge <hi>Hale</hi> did, in the times of Uſurpation, to maintain Property. 'Tis true, Subjects have Liberty in all things, where they are not reſtrain'd by Laws, and in ſuch things they have reſtrain'd themſelves. As too furious Uſe of Power has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger'd many States, ſo the want of Power has ruin'd others.</p>
            <p>But, as there is nothing weaker than to think, that any Government will be baffled by Private men; ſo, upon this Diſcretion, the Peace of every Nation depends; which is the greateſt Earthly Bleſſing.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:107015:49"/>
            <p>And, if I do ſay, the Peace of moſt men depends upon the Uſe of their own Reaſon, I think 'tis no Paradox: 'tis the want thereof puts us many times, (uncompell'd) upon <hi>accidental Juries;</hi> where, very often, Paſſion, Malice, or ſecret Intereſt ſwayes; or the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Judges, or their cowardiſe, or want of Patience to hear; or, which is too frequent, <hi>the mercenary impudence of ſome Pleaders;</hi> or, which happens ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Courts of Equity; where, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Judge be very able, the Barr will run round him, and abuſe his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, to the ruin of the unfortunate Plaintiff or Defendant.</p>
            <p>And, though I may appeal to moſt men of Buſineſs, for the Warranty of theſe general Inſtances, yet, becauſe the Gent. is guilty of uncivil Excurſions from the Text, he undertakes to confute: I will diſcover the Fox, that Vulgar Eyes may ſee his unkind wiles, to evade the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's fair Intentions with labour'd Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:107015:50"/>
            <p>Purſuant to which Deſign, the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er may pleaſe to obſerve, what Pains he takes in half a dozen Pages, of his <hi>Plain Dealing,</hi> to tell our Author the neceſſary Conſequences of taking Religion quite away from the World, by removing it, as he calls it, out of the minds of men, which no man will deny (if it were poſſible to baniſh it) but whether he had any reaſon to huff, with all that Harangue, from any ſlip of the <hi>Author's,</hi> I leave all Ingenuous Perſons to judge, conſidering the whole thread of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi>'s Book: for, where the Author ſayes if ſuch Pretences (meaning Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Religion, not Religion it ſelf) were removed, by granting Liberty of Conſcience every where; I ſay, ſuch Liberty, as do's not hinder Peace and Trade, the cauſe of moſt Wars and Bloodſhed would be removed; the Cauſe, I ſay again, of moſt Foreign and Civil Wars.</p>
            <p>This to prove, I may inſtance the War by <hi>the Spaniard in</hi> 88. <hi>againſt</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>the Iriſh Rebellion in the Queens time:</hi> and more dreadful in ours, <hi>the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:107015:50"/>direful Effects of the</hi> Scotiſh <hi>Covenant,</hi> the preſent Stirs in <hi>Hungary, &amp;c.</hi> all which evince the Truth of our <hi>Author's</hi> Argument.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>French</hi> King's Actions, be they the effects of Ambition or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; yet this is plain, there is a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Darkneſs endeavour'd to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by the dark, cunning, and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatigable Induſtry of it's Emiſſaries and <hi>Bigots</hi> every where; and very wiſe, loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al perſons, do aſcribe much of our peace, ſince the happy Reſtauration of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King, to his being freed from hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring of uncharitable Zealots even amongſt our ſelves at home.</p>
            <p>Nor need I reckon up <hi>Ziſca's Actions;</hi> nor the Ravage of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> under <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> the Effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Blood by <hi>Duke D'alva,</hi> who put 18000. <hi>to death</hi> in cold Blood, (having toucht the indiſcreet Zeal of his Maſter <hi>Philip</hi> already,) nor the miſguided Zeal of our <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> nor the prodigious Fortune of <hi>O. C.</hi> in his Pretences for Religion, nor his Actions complying with ſuch a Vizard: yet it may not be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:107015:51"/>amiſs to remember the Breach of that League the <hi>Hungarians</hi> had made with <hi>Amarath</hi> the third, the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> King; how 'twas broken by the religious heat of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Legate, which was the cauſe of ſhedding ſo much Chriſtian Blood, and God was pleas'd to give the <hi>Turk</hi> Victory after three days Fight, and the <hi>Othoman's</hi> appeal to Chriſt for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and we muſt not forget the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in <hi>Peimont</hi> of late years, upon the ſcore of Religion, not to ſpeak of particular Maſſacres occaſion'd from Biggotiſm, whereof Hiſtories are ſo full, 'tis not neceſſary to inſert them in this Paper, nor would I have ſo far waded in Particulars, but to ſhew and expoſe the <hi>Gent</hi>'s. unreaſonable Confidence on the other hand inferring, that moſt of our late Wars have ariſen upon purely politick Pretenſions, and not upon reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Colors.</p>
            <p>And I not only hope, but am really perſuaded, it will never be within the Power, nor Deſign of any diſſenting party in <hi>England,</hi> (ſo men be not too much proſecuted for Nonconformity) to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107015:51"/>ſtir up my Country-men into actual Diſobedience againſt his Majeſties Laws, farther than to ſuffer: for the Scars of the late inteſtine Wars, remaining ſtill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freſh in Memory, the greateſt Convulſions the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Empire ever felt (which I hope never will be renew'd) being hardly yet ſhak'd off.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this general Toleration to all Proteſtants which I ſeem to plead for, at leaſt wiſh, if Authority ſhall think fit, may ſeem of Right, indulgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible to that ſort of men, who claim their Religion under a foreign Head. The Anſwer is eaſie, <hi>viz.</hi> That 'tis not for their Religion, but for deſigning to alter the Government, and for drawing off his Majeſty's Subjects to the Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, they are corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by our Laws; which Laws, when ſtrain'd by paſſionate Judges, beyond the Intention of former Legiſlators, to the Oppreſſion of peaceable diſſenting Proteſtants, gratifie ill men, hinder Trade, ſcandalize the Proteſtant Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es beyond the Seas, and ſeem to deſerve a Parliamentary Explanation.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:107015:52"/>
            <p>However, our Diffenters are to know, there muſt always be, and ever ſince Chriſtianity was embrac'd by Princes, there has been, general Rules authorized for the Church, whereby <hi>Indecencies</hi> have been puniſh'd, which are judg'd ſo to be ſuch, by the Supreme Authority in all States, relating to the external way of honouring God; and becauſe Peace is the end of Government, men's opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, when publickly vented and found inconſiſtent with Peace, muſt be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Magiſtrate, which is not to make men ſee double by being dazl'd betwixt Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal powers, for all Power is temporal, as Power.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, as <hi>T. H.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Paul or Cephas,</hi> or <hi>Apollo may he followed, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps as the beſt way, according to a mans li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſo it be done without Contention, and without meaſuring the Doctrine of Chriſt by our Affection to the perſon of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> (the Fault which <hi>Paul</hi> reprehended in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>) his Reaſons follow, See the <hi>Leviathan ch.</hi> 47. <hi>pag.</hi> 385. and they are ſuch as no man has ever hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:107015:52"/>preſum'd to refute; though his ſworn Enemies have aſſaulted him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe by Shoals.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> are loth to venture their Salvations at Croſs and Pile; which <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> urges in his Chapter, <hi>de fide,</hi> a little too eagerly.</p>
            <p>Let us take heed, <hi>Since the Tares muſt grow up with the Wheat till the Harveſt,</hi> leaſt by furious Zeal, we be found guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of plucking up the Wheat with the Tares.</p>
            <p>And let us remember our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Cenſure of thoſe who requir'd Fire from Heaven, to conſume the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent Unkindneſſes of, perhaps, (in ſome meaſure) ignorant men; he tells his Diſciples, <hi>they knew not what Spirit they were of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis as hard to be virtuous, as to be whipt into any particular Religion; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our natural paſſions are contrary to the Laws of reaſon: and for that, the Vices of ſome of the Clergy, on both ſides, have render'd them contemptible, for which laſt, God has, more than once, removed the Candleſtick.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:107015:53"/>
            <p>The Object of their Profeſſion being properly, Eternal Life; the people think, and truly, they ought not to inter-med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with Government, at leaſt in the Pulpit: <hi>England</hi> has felt the ill Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of their Excurſions more than once, and what Prejudice the <hi>Spaniard</hi> has gotten, and how he has dwindl'd in Power, by his bloody and perverted Inquiſition and blind Zeal, otherwiſe, he that runs may read.</p>
            <p>What Liberty the <hi>Turk</hi> allows to peaceable Chriſtians in his Empire, is well known, and how he thrives by it, has been here hinted before.</p>
            <p>We are near enough to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> to underſtand their Permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to Conſcience, and the Advance of their politick Intereſts thereby, which never lyes.</p>
            <p>The Seat of Power is abſolute there, and every where, therefore a <hi>Lenitive Law</hi> is not impracticable here, in reaſon, if our Superiors pleaſe, nor inconſiſtent with our Government Regal.</p>
            <p>The Church depends upon the State not the State upon the Church, for the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:107015:53"/>King is Head of both, and they both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re conſolidate in him, <hi>Jure Coronae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All Kings, as Kings, were originally veſted with that Power, ſo the Pope, in his own Dition, has it <hi>Jure Papatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some ſay, Nothing is Conſcience to any man, which ought not to be ſo to another; 'tis regularly true, I think, and though, ſure, he that ſaid, <hi>Tales pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly told and allow'd, was Religion,</hi> ſpake wittily, relating to Sacred Hiſtory; yet, methinks, 'twas ſomething below his Gravity, it was a Definition a little too jocular, but that Gentleman ſpake of Religion in General.</p>
            <p>However, ſince the <hi>Gent.</hi> in his <hi>Plain Dealing,</hi> has diſcover'd his diſlike of <hi>T. H.</hi> I may take leave to ſay, I think him a moſt excellent Philoſopher, and Great in ſeveral other reſpects; for warranty whereof, I need only produce that admirable <hi>Pindarick Ode</hi> upon him, written by my School-fellow <hi>Cowley,</hi> where he ſaith,
<q>
                  <l>There's none but God does know,</l>
                  <l>Whether the fair <hi>Idaea</hi> thou doſt ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Agrees intirely with thine own, or no.</l>
               </q> Speaking of T. H.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:107015:54"/>
            <p>'Tis ſuch an <hi>Ode,</hi> as perhaps excells all made before it, and I ſhall think it true, till I ſee a fairer <hi>Idaea</hi> of Truth, and no longer: for it is not my purpoſe to be an obſtinate <hi>Heretick,</hi> no nor a <hi>State-Martyr</hi> neither. Nor to ſuffer at all for Diſobedience to Laws. I take him to be the beſt Subject, who obeys them; not him, who patiently yields to pay the Penalties; Paſſive Obedience, and Free Will, are ſenſe alike to my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why ſhould a man be miſerable before his time?</hi> was the Queſtion of the Wiſe King.</p>
            <p>I do think, 'tis beſt to be of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of a man's Countrey, Externally at leaſt; and ſure I am, there is nothing morally evil in ours: and for External Worſhip in Religion, as to time and place, it is determinable by the Supreme Magiſtrate (in my opinion) not as a Chriſtian, but as King. For neither the Brazen Serpent, nor the Golden Calf, were naturally preferrible one more than another; 'twas <hi>Moſes</hi> gave the Precedency. Betwixt the Laws of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:107015:54"/>Reaſon (which are undoubtedly God's Eternal Laws) and the Laws of a man's Civil Sovereign, which we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to obey, I know none; <hi>the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law being but a repetition of the Laws of Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Conſideration gives me occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſlight the huge Volumes of ſtuff obtruded upon us, otherwiſe, imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, <hi>as grounded upon the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but without any warrant to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us, as Chriſtians and Subjects; to believe the Authors of ſuch waſte Papers, in what they write. All this while, every good man is to conſider the moſt Excellent Counſels of cur Saviour, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in the New Teſtament, and the Hiſtory of God's Divine Providence in the old.</p>
            <p>Herein we agree; but I do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what the <hi>Gent.</hi> means by the Laws of the Church: for the Church of <hi>England</hi> never did, nor can make any Law, nor is it Rational to ſay ſhe can, for when Laws are made, they are the King's Laws, and the Biſhops are his Biſhops.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:107015:55"/>
            <p>And if all the Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> had been dead, when the King was reſtor'd, (there did not above three ſurvive the Uſurpation, as I am inform'd) unleſs the King had been pleas'd to grant his <hi>Licentiam Eligendi,</hi> there could have been no new ones made. His Majeſty, in his Natural Capacity, is the <hi>Cauſa ſine quâ non.</hi> This ſtrikes off the Explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Pretence of the Biſhops <hi>Jus devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and for their <hi>Politicum,</hi> they were better without it. Let the Parliament judge, as to their Legal Rights.</p>
            <p>But, whether the greateſt part of our Diſſenters go to Meetings, out of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to carry on their Trades, and not out of Religion, (which the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſaith they do) I know not: Probably they do: and 'tis as true, that many go to our Churches for ſuch Ends, or worſe. Let every man examine himſelf, and, by the Lives of each ſort, judge which are moſt probably Atheiſtical; it being hard to believe, that they who live in adviſed ſins, do really believe there is any God at all, let them be of what Party they pleaſe.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:107015:55"/>
            <p>As for my own part, I am apt to think, there are with us two main and Evident Cauſes of Atheiſm: The firſt is, the Example of Great Men and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; the ſecond is, the Debauchery of ſome Miniſters, eſpecially in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys far off <hi>London:</hi> for, in and about <hi>London,</hi> to ſpeak candidly, I find many worthy Preachers, and vertuous men; but how the Flights and Mountees of the <hi>Gent.</hi> againſt Atheiſm, came to be inſerted into <hi>Plain Dealing,</hi> as in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to our Author, I cannot tell, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were to ſhew his floſculous Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; much good may it do him, he is a Plain-dealing Perſon: but the plain truth is, the midling ſort of men will not be brought to reſt with an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Faith in their authoriz'd Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; that will not do in <hi>England:</hi> the People apprehend well enough, for they feel ſooneſt; ſo far <hi>Vox populi</hi> is <hi>Vox Dei.</hi> 'Tis the mediation of Reaſon muſt convince them, and reduce them, or the ſpecial Revelation of Gods Spirit, which, how eaſily miſtaken, is eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; I ſay, miſtaken by ſuch, who
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:107015:56"/>take their own Dreams for the Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p>All mens Condeſcentions, Adheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and Procedures in Moral, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Politick Affairs, being built upon what they think Reaſon, and no otherwiſe, which needs no illuſtration to a direct Atheiſt; for he, disbelieving a Deity, gives no Adoration: to a mere Pagan, for he, probably, gives it to Sun or Moon, and yet thinks they are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Powers: to one of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, for he takes the Pope to be infallible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to any Diſſenter; for if his diſſenting proceed from Conſcience, it proceeds from his Reaſon: So the Merchant, and all other Tradeſmen are directed, and conducted by that which ſeems the moſt Rational way towards their reſpective Ends. Yet the <hi>Gent.</hi> is pleas'd to term the Author's Argument, proving, invincibly, the neceſſity of our Appeal to Humane Reaſon, <hi>a fooliſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</hi> But ſome are too haſty to wear Swords.</p>
            <p>I might add, that Obedience is more chearfully and rationally given to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:107015:56"/>from their Subjects, from their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing protected by their Princes: Self-preſervation being an eſſential part of the Law of Nature, and involves the Summary of the Laws of Reaſon, to do as a man would be done unto; for if I abuſe my Power, there are Arms ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than mine.</p>
            <p>And as things are, (in my poor Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) at this Juncture, it comports beſt with the Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and conſequently with the King's Intereſt, (whoſe Greatneſs and Safety is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in the Riches and Strength of his Subjects) that all Diſſenting Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, about the External Worſhip of God (for Opinions may be, and will be internally free) ſhould be kept, as near as can be, in a Balance (the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> excepted, ſo far as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Government, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, 'tis ſaid, they would bring in a Foreign Head;) all which <hi>W. Penn</hi> has ſubſtantially proved, in a little Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe lately publiſhed, and diſpers'd into moſt Parliament mens hands by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which, to ſpeak truly, is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:107015:57"/>candidly, and juiciouſſy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, and with a good Maſculine Style, free from Canting; which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offering violence to Reaſon, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be anſwered: for it is proved from the Laws of Reaſon, from Scripture, from the Laws of Nations generally, and from thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> and relates to Eternal Happineſs after this Life, as well as to Temporals. Beſides, I am very well ſatisfied, the Scale of Trade would never have held, as it has here, ſince the King came in, if the Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers had been rigorouſly puniſhed in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Center of Commerce.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, now that the Diſſenting Parties are fix'd under their reſpective Miniſters, into a kind of Corporate So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, and their Miniſters live by it: it may be ſuppos'd it will be more difficult, every day than other, to make ſuch a <hi>Comprehenſive Law</hi> (as is deſir'd by the moſt Prudent men) to bear well at this time: As to that, the Parliament can cure it well enough, with the Permiſſion of the King, and by apt Qualifications and Reſtrictions, if it pleaſes. And, I
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:107015:57"/>am inform'd, Judge <hi>Hale</hi> did draw an Act for that end, which Sir <hi>Orlando Bridgman</hi> put him upon: but there is a Time for every thing, and God's Time is the beſt time. And now to return to our Province, that the Gent. may not think I have forgot him.</p>
            <p>I muſt preſume to tell him, his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer does contain many other frivolous Objections, impertinent Stories, wild, and illogical Concluſions, deduc'd from precarious Principles, or totally Foreign to our Author's Treatiſe and Deſign; which, I cannot hold my ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to reply. Neither did I ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or undertake to obey the Gent. in ſuch invitations, nor to follow him in ſuch extravagant Proceſſions; for I hold it loſs of time, and a kind of ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the Reader's Ears.</p>
            <p>We are indeed too much peſter'd with Books, every day creeping abroad, ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> by paſſionate men, which ſignifie nothing.</p>
            <p>But the Deſign of our <hi>Author</hi> was, in Appearance at leaſt, pious and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to pacifie all parties in Religion,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:107015:58"/>I mean all Proteſtants, of what <hi>Species</hi> ſoever, here in <hi>England,</hi> with a Lenitive both charitable and rational, which may ſeem now ſeaſonable, ſince it's found by Experience, ſuch Corroſives as have been applyed, prove altogether ineffectual. And let us conſider mature<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Wiſh of <hi>Moſes, I would that all God's people were Prophets,</hi> the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our bleſſed Saviour in chiding of his Diſciples, <hi>Who ask'd Fire from Heaven &amp;c.</hi> of St. Paul's <hi>being all things to all men,</hi> that of following <hi>Paul, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas or Apollo,</hi> and the Patterns of the Primitive Times of the Church, when preaching was, as it ought to be now, catechetical, not theatrical. I ſay, let us conſider, if all the Cauſes and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before ſparſedly given in this Reply, and the Complexion of things, do not ſeem to conſpire for a legal Plaſter, to cure that incancerating Humor of vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another about Trifles, at leaſt, Indifferencies, compar'd to the Elements of Chriſtianity, or to the Eſſence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Good Laws, and well executed, to ſuppreſs Vice, will keep all ſteady; let
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:107015:58"/>the old Gentleman at <hi>Rome,</hi> be as angry as he pleaſes, he has got nothing by us of late; and had he ſeen the throng, in our Streets, of ſtout Fellows, when his <hi>Effigies</hi> was burnt laſt, 'twould have made him deſpair of being able to rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle in here.</p>
            <p>The Nation is well rouz'd up, and we have a Wiſe Prince, able to judge of Exigencies: all the little Shams and pretended Plots, I ſay, pretended Plots, of ill-affected men, of all ſorts, to the Government, begin to dwindle, and look as they indeed are, ridiculous. How far the main Deſign of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries does ſtill advance, and by what Artifices, Authority muſt judge, and does, I doubt not, take Care to prevent the Miſchief.</p>
            <p>Now as to our Deſign in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, I hope enough hath been ſaid to ſatisfie all ingenious men, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudic'd, that <hi>Reaſon</hi> is the ſafeſt Guide; and conſequently, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that moſt ingenious, much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, and fortunate Treatiſe, entitled <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> well deſerves the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulation
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:107015:59"/>of every judicious perſon, for his Pains in compoſing it.</p>
            <p>As to the Reader of this Paper, I ſhall not (as the Author of <hi>Plain dealing</hi> does) implore his reaſonable and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Cenſure (though I know 'tis a very critical Age) becauſe if he that reads be rational, I am ſure I ſhall have it; if he be otherwiſe, I cannot have it, therefore I will not ask it.</p>
            <p>Nor will I counterbuff the <hi>Gent.</hi> with <hi>Grub-ſtreet</hi> Poetry, in Oppoſition to his Comical <hi>Ralpho,</hi> though I can do it with as nimble a <hi>Sarcaſme;</hi> it being at beſt, only a gentile kind of Buffoon'ry, ſomething like the Rymes which the Parſon of <hi>Pentlow,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> when he was ſeventy at leaſt, told me he tyed in Paper about a Buzards Neck, taken a little before in Lime-twigs, which had ſnatcht away one of his Goſslings, and which follows here.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The Parſon of <hi>Pentlow</hi> that now is,</l>
               <l>For ſtealing of one poor Goſling of his,</l>
               <l>Has ſeal'd up mine Eyes, and ſtich'd up my Bum,</l>
               <l>And bid me go fly to the day of Doom.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:107015:59"/>
            <p>What became of the Buzard ſo uſed, after ſhe had ſpent her Wings, I never heard, but if it were <hi>plain,</hi> it was not fair <hi>dealing</hi> from a man of his Coat to be ſo cruel to the hungry Bird.</p>
            <p>Neither was it Charity in the <hi>Gent.</hi> we oppoſe, to deſign the ſwitching out of our <hi>Author</hi>'s Light, becauſe he ſaw farther into a Mill-ſtone than other men, and taught the Geeſe how to avoid the Fox, by perching upon the tree of Life; <hi>Reaſon,</hi> whoſe Fruit, when taken into a Stomach, not overcharg'd with Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, always purifies the Brain.</p>
            <p>I have done with the <hi>Gent.</hi> and having a ſmall Book juſt now ſent me by a very ingenious Lady, deſignedly written by a <hi>Romaniſt</hi> to ſtrike our Author dead; I read it over and found it fill'd up with Arguments of Univerſality, Tradition, and Infallibility of that Church, <hi>Peter</hi>'s Authority <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all theſe larded with Zeal to perſuade me into a Dependance and Reliance upon the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as the true one; in which Treatiſe that Author boldly ſaid, my Reaſon ought to Acquieſce, 'tis well that ſide alſo makes Reaſon the Judge.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:107015:60"/>
            <p>I was pleas'd with the ſound of the Word, more than with his reaſons, for they did not ſatisfie my Underſtanding: yet had I known that Authors <hi>Genius</hi> inclin'd to Poetry, I would have recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him, for Inſtruction, to, my old Friend the Parſon of <hi>Pentlow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I begin to think my ſelf fortunate, having hitherto ſided with a noble Captain (for ſo I account <hi>Humane Reaſon</hi>) which 'tis confeſt, every ſide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to, and which may poſſibly be beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from it's <hi>Poſts</hi> by the clatter of ſome <hi>Coffee-houſe,</hi> but it will always recover and baffle its greateſt <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> at the long run: for Truth is ſtrongeſt, but Reaſon does aſſure it, without whoſe gentle Mediation and Midwifry, we had ſtill remain'd in the State of War, and conſequently, had been miſerable.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="review">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:107015:60"/>
            <head>A RE-VIEW AND APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>OUR Reply having been written now above two years, I have re-conſider'd it, and, from the paſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Affairs, and preſent, do think it neceſſary to add this <hi>Re-view,</hi> and other Amplifications, as either ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to the Deſign, or otherwiſe material; inſiſting upon the Proſpect of Reaſon, and the ill conſequence of neglecting its guidance, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That, from the Petulancy, Heat, and unſeaſonable Eagerneſs of ſome, not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diſcreet nor Learned; and of others,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:107015:61"/>Learned, Honeſt, and generally Prudent, but not infallible, occaſion is taken, by the other ſide, to anſwer, upon ſuch Provocations, as they can, alledging, that their Sufferings are, and have been, all along, for Conſcience-ſake, and for well-doing, though the Letters of the Laws are againſt them, a Plea ever fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd in all Ages.</p>
            <p>That theſe Diſputes about <hi>Externals</hi> onely, (for both Parties agree in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Doctrine) are miſchievous to us at home, and ſcandalous to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches abroad beyond the Seas.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, if it gets no Proſelytes from theſe unſeaſonable Heats, yet it has great reaſon to be pleas'd therewith; for ſhe thrives by our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; and can thrive by no other means here now.</p>
            <p>That that Church was more Politick (while ſhe had as fair hopes as ever, to prevail after the Queens death) by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying outwardly with our Laws: for, till the 12th of <hi>Q. Eliz.</hi> all, or moſt <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> did, and were
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:107015:61"/>permitted by the Pope, to go to our Proteſtant Churches, to hear the Service, receive the Sacrament, and take the Oath of Allegeance; though ſince, the Jeſuits procur'd a Bull of Inhibition, for their own profit, yet, 'twas never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted any Crime for a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> at that time, not to go, or to go to the Proteſtant Church: whence, our want of Charity, to the Diſſenters, appears leſs, than that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, our Policy leſs, and our uneaſineſs too viſible thereby.</p>
            <p>Neither are the Diſſenters altogether excuſable, in their too ſtiff Separation, and boggling at ſmall things; but I will be ſparing in judging tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; nevertheleſs it is obvious, That from our pernicious Diviſions, ſo dangerous to our Religion, and becauſe, tho the firſt Reformers went a good ſtep, yet <hi>no great progreſs has lately been made towards the Reaſon of our departure from</hi> Rome, <hi>and reforming things amiſs,</hi> moderate men on both ſides here, do wiſh for ſome new Laws, to conſolidate the Conformiſts, and Non-conformiſts,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:107015:62"/>in ſome meaſure; or, at leaſt, that ſome Ceremonies might be left: and for the Explanation of ſome Laws now in force, or limiting the force of others, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of that for impoſing twenty pounds <hi>per</hi> Month, for not coming to Church; which Law, I ſuppoſe no Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer doubts, was originally intended againſt the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and not againſt <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> who were few then; and 'twas the <hi>Roman</hi> Party at that time which confronted the Laws, and begot the Statute.</p>
            <p>The next Obſervation relates to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications:</hi> which, how familiarly decreed, and for what ſlight Cauſes, and upon what gainful Deſigns; and conſequently, how prejudicial to many of his Majeſtie's good Subjects, and how contrary to its Primitive and Grave In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, all Wiſe and Honeſt men of this Nation are, and have been long, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible of, and of the ruine of ſome Families, and the inriching of ill Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, by ſuch Methods.</p>
            <p>But, may ſome ſay, the Statute of <hi>Q. Mary</hi> againſt <hi>diſturbers of Preachers,</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:107015:62"/>is partly in force, and of Uſe, which was principally intended againſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; for they were the Perſons likely to diſturb the Romaniſh Preachers then, wherefore they ſay, Why is not that of <hi>Eliz.</hi> alſo to be put in conſtant practiſe, it being a general Law, and provides for Peace?</p>
            <p>Our Anſwer is, The Caſe is alter'd; for, <hi>though equal Principles do lead to equal Ends, 'tis but when the matter about which we are converſant is equal:</hi> And now the Papiſts are the moſt dangerous to our Peace, and do plot to that end, if we may credit King and Parliament, or our own Eyes; therefore that Law of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> againſt Recuſancy ſtands in force; yet it ſeems to want ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination; and that of <hi>Mary,</hi> being in part repeal'd, is continu'd, as to the diſturbing of Preachers, <hi>the true Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Law being the Will of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many other antiquated, and, as things are, inconvenient Laws, Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, which I have not room to remark here; and as to
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:107015:63"/>the brangling practick part of both Courts, the Judges may, at leaſt, they ought to correct it: tho one ſaid wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, yet truly, <hi>that no body but themſelves</hi> (meaning the Civil Practiſers) <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands their Practiſe</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid Laws) <hi>nor themſelves neither.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the Practiſe at Common Law, depending upon great Officers, as ſome ſay; if ſo, 'tis all dark.</p>
            <p>This, however, ſince we are upon Diſcourſe of Reaſon, I'll venture to ſay, 'tis evident, that, too often, the Clients are tortur'd betwixt <hi>Prohibitions</hi> and <hi>Conſultations;</hi> ſo dangerous and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome it is, where Courts do ſtrive for Juriſdiction: ſo alſo, where the Judge's Power increaſes, and the <hi>Jury</hi>'s decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or is over-aw'd: <hi>for where Judges</hi> (as has been our Caſe in <hi>Richard</hi> the Second's time) <hi>preſume to determine, or delay by diſcretion, or border upon the thing call'd perverſion, upon miſapply'd Maxims,</hi> (which, I hope will not be our Caſe:) <hi>Thoſe Nations are more at eaſe, where their Laws are unwritten (ſuppoſing the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Laws of Reaſon;)</hi> and which
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:107015:63"/>minds me of the familiar and exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Practiſe of ſome (as a wiſe Lord lately call'd them) <hi>Trading Juſtices,</hi> by their granting Warrants upon eaſie, or unprov'd Suggeſtions, (above 10000 having been made out in one year by one of them lately, which I can prove;) inſomuch, as few honeſt, modeſt men can be free from their diſcretional Laſh: which is a <hi>Gravamen,</hi> I think, and may, or ought to be prevented by a new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troductory Law; for, I ſuppoſe, the Common Law is too dull to do it; or the Medicine, that way, has given place to the Diſeaſe: for the Remedy by an Action againſt the Juſtice, is worſe than the Diſeaſe, ſince their awe upon Juries, from their abuſed Power, to the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of the Government, and thereby, to the indiſpoſing of Subjects from their due and peaceable obedience to the Laws, wherein Religion properly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts: And as to our Reply,</p>
            <p>Whereas the Gentleman boldly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd, but never prov'd, the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of Atheiſm, by the reliance upon Reaſon, which I have refuted, and ſhew'd
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:107015:64"/>who were two of the moſt probable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troductors of it; I think fit to add a third Cauſe of irreligion, if not Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm; namely, the daily Printing and publiſhing many Tranſlations, and other Books, which preſume to treat of the inexplicable Myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion, and of God; which indeed fall not under Humane Capacity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine Logically; and whereby, in ſtead of reconciling that, which they call Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, to the Doctrine of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, or remarking upon both Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, they render the plain Truths thereof, not only to the Vulgar, but to ſome pedantically Learned men, ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. Such is, the now publickly ſold, <hi>Spinoſa</hi>'s Tractate, which does hurt; and if I ſhould ſay, <hi>D. Cud. Repetitions</hi> alſo, poſſibly 'twere true, though the Dr. meant well, and is very Learned.</p>
            <p>The Contemplation whereof, obliges me to add a fourth Cauſe of Irreligion, if not Atheiſm; which is, that ſeveral Books of late years have been <hi>Licens'd,</hi> even by the Univerſities, bearing glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Titles, the Subject matter whereof,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:107015:64"/>does unhinge the Foundations of our Reveal'd Religion, whereof one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance may be in a celebrated Folio, wherein, amongſt other wild Opinions, 'tis poſitively ſaid, and often inſiſted, that the Soul of man, before its attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Heaven, muſt paſs through, (and run the hazard of being bewil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and ſuffocated in) thick, gelid Vapours, dusky Clouds, and other ſuch like, which, though the Learned may digeſt ſafely, yet ordinary men, who have been taught that the Soul of a good man paſſes immediately from Earth to Heaven, after death, (without ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termediate Probations, Purifications and Puniſhments,) are apt either to lean, from ſuch infuſions, towards the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Purgatory, or to think, there is no proper dependance upon our Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme of Religion; or, which is more probable, from ſuch <hi>Chimaera</hi>'s of the Learned, to think, that Religion it ſelf is nothing elſe but a Politick Device. Theſe Books, I ſay, ſo authoriz'd, or Printed otherwiſe, are the bane of Unwary, and eſpecially young men,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:107015:65"/>not able truely to weigh matters, nor to take in ſuch Pills without chewing of them. And theſe are the fruits of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uberant Fancies, not grounded either upon Reaſon or Scripture, whereof I might give a thouſand inſtances.</p>
            <p>Moreover, whereas I have hinted, in my <hi>Reply,</hi> that our Diſſenters ought to underſtand the neceſſity of ſome Laws for the Government of the Church; I ſhould have added, that the Conformiſt Miniſters, by ſeveral Diſcourſes of many Perſons, Eminent for their Degrees and Parts, have beſt defended Proteſtantiſm againſt its Adverſaries of late, tho it does not therefore follow, but that ſome better Progreſſions may be made; and if her Out-works and Guards grow crazy, or become languid, by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much watching, it may be neceſſary to repair the one, and reinforce the other, with detachments from her disbanded, yet valiant, and politick Officers.</p>
            <p>For, where Workmen or Souldiers are left, or put out of Employment, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preſumption that there's no occaſion to uſe their help, (if there happen to be
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:107015:65"/>occaſion for their aſſiſtance by a ſudden irruption of the Enemy;) 'tis not only convenient, but neceſſary to take them into Service again, unleſs their former Unfaithfulneſs have render'd them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally unworthy, or uncapable: Now, whether the preſent time requires the whole ſtrength of our Friends, or not; or, whether the Nonconformiſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are fit to be conſidered as Friends, upon the main, who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> belov'd of the greateſt number of Civil People, are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally moral men, and are oblig'd, in point of Intereſt, and otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, to oppoſe the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> I muſt leave Authority in Parliament to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and I doubt not but the thing will be conſider'd there, with all the imaginable Duty, and rational Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations to His Majeſty, with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt reſpect to his Imperial Crown and Dignity, which ought to be the wiſh and Prayer of all Proteſtants: and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, the undoubted truth of this <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm</hi> may inforce the Conſult, <hi>viz. That where the Danger of any action out-weighs the probable profit, 'tis no wiſdom to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:107015:66"/>it: but where the poſſible profit out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighs the Danger, 'tis imprudence to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, whether theſe <hi>Inſtances</hi> will be pleaſing to men otherwiſe influenc'd by Intereſt, or miſguided by the Artifice of others, not truly <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it does not much concern me: for I am well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, by <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> that they need no other proofs of their veracity, to all knowing and good Subjects, than their bare Prolations (yet I do but propound (as I think) what is Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.)</p>
            <p>Purſuant to my Deſign; No man queſtions, but that Peace is the proper end of Government, ſo 'tis admitted, that the Magiſtrate is Judge of the ways and methods which conduce to that end; nor is it deny'd by any that pretends to Senſe, but that Opinions, if contrary to Peace, (in the Judgment of the Supreme Magiſtrate) may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated, becauſe mens Actions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly follow their Opinions: and, 'tis experimentally true, that our Diviſions about ſmall things, do weaken the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:107015:66"/>Cauſe; and it follows thence, that rigid and indiſcreet, ſtarcht and poſitive men of all ſides, relating to the External part of Worſhip, are the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of Peace.</p>
            <p>Next theſe, follow the fooliſh, yet dangerous <hi>Atheiſts, who are the onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels againſt God,</hi> with which Diſeaſe, whoever is tinctur'd, is ready, if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to ſhake off all obedience to his Vicegerents upon Earth, and, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, to reduce Mankind to the ſtate of War, which is Anarchy; and againſt which Poyſon, I have proved, Reaſon to be the onely Antidote: whence it naturally follows, that all thoſe who daily, by Diſcourſe and Writings, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly ſtrive, not onely to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>Baſis</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> but to cancell the undoubted and Eternal obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of Natural Religion, are Enemies to Peace; and without which conviction (which begot all Covenants, the very foundations of Property) no fear of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or future Puniſhments, for violation of ſuch Covenants, can be at all; and thence, all obedience to Humane Laws
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:107015:67"/>will decay, if it ſhall ſeem againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. I ſuppoſe therefore, it mainly concerns the Supreme Magiſtrate, as well in his Natural, as Politick Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by <hi>all poſſible condeſcentions,</hi> upon emergent occaſions, and By-laws, in time, and Penally, to obviate the growth of ſuch idle Diſcourſes, as threaten the diſſolution of Government it ſelf; unto which end, there can be no ſuch direction as Humane Reaſon, whoſe Excellency I defend, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prove, not onely to be the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, but the onely guide, with due helps out of Gods revealed Will; which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Reaſon teaches to underſtand, and apply.</p>
            <p>Beſides, It is the Magiſtrate's true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt ſo to provide, by prevention, who can never be ſupported, but muſt fail, when either he wants Power <hi>de facto,</hi> (which all fiery Zelots of any ſide would circumſcribe) to diſcharge his Duty to God and Man; or ſhall be oblig'd to part with any of his neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and eſſential Rights of Sovereignty, (whereof want of Money is alwayes the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:107015:67"/>Parent) and which makes me think, that no man can be judg'd a good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, nor a Lover of that Government, (under which we have liv'd for ſo many Ages happily) who deſigns ſuch Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to his King, as may hinder the diſcharge of his Truſt, as a King. Nor can any man be accounted a good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor to his Prince, who ſhall adviſe ſuch wayes, (tho never ſo ſpecious) as, if followed, may leſſen his Maſter's Reputation of ſincere Care and Study for the Preſervation of his Subjects; to which Diſtemper, ſo pernicious and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to the beſt Princes, (where their Favourites are falſe or weak) 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible a great General Councel (whoſe Safety is involv'd in the Safety of their King) can be obnoxious, conſidering the Elements of ſuch a Councel, for whoſe Seſſion and Progreſſion, all men, not conſcious of ill Actions towards the Publick weal of their Native Countrey, really pray.</p>
            <p>Yet I will not deny, but ſome others ought to be rather convinc'd by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than accus'd for Malignancy againſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:107015:68"/>the Publick: ſuch are thoſe, who take wrong meaſures, and create, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, unneceſſary Fears, from our late Abuſes, in the times of Civil Wars here, and of that Uſurped Power, by a ſort of Maſterleſs, and ill men, <hi>to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and indelible Infamy of our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nation; tho, God knows, it was againſt the will of the greateſt, and moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part thereof.</hi> Such are others, and poſſibly well-meaning men, who, from the inutility of another now diſſolv'd long P. ſince, (to ſay no worſe) or from the ill Complexion of Affairs now, and difficulty of Cure by Parliamentary Methods; or from the immoderate Heat of ſome, too many, Great, but young men, who, probably, have not well conſider'd the Late Civil Wars, nor the Danger and Incivility of too eagerly preſſing the Sovereign Power to unſeaſonable Conceſſions, not of abſolute Neceſſity, or upon other more remote or diſtantial Fears, whoſe Effects to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate, only lies in the Power of God: or from what other Cauſes I know not, that they and other men become oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:107015:68"/>to the general deſires of all thoſe, who are ſatisfied, that no other means can be found out to ſet us right every way, but a true underſtanding in P. betwixt his Majeſty and his People: for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing us from the moſt unkind, unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd, indefatigable, and induſtrious Deſigns of all ſuch, who either, blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by furious Zeal, moved by Intereſt, or, which is worſt of all (and which I am loth to believe) out of mere ſpite, leave no ſtone unturn'd, to introduce a Foreign Juriſdiction, tho hitherto, thanks be to God, ſuch Concuſſions have rather fix'd and awaken'd us, than weaken'd our Foundations, both Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Religious; for whoſe ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to ſpeak humanely, we are more beholding to his Majeſty, to the brave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Gentry and City, than to the Zeal of ſome others, as much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd by their Intereſt, if they could ſee it.</p>
            <p>But, as to that Pretence, that our Laws are already ſo good, as there needs no better; certain it is, there is, and always has been, and will be, from the nature
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:107015:69"/>of Laws themſelves, Cauſes and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents (which no Humane Laws, nor the Wit or Reaſon of any Body of Men could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore-ſee) to explain, alter, and enact new Laws; unto which ends, if there be any better way or method than Humane Reaſon, I would be glad to underſtand it; and then, and not till till then, I ſhall ſtand convinc'd, that what the <hi>Gent.</hi> I oppoſe, has offer'd in diſparagement thereof, is cogent. But, if Reaſon be the onely way to ſettle Peace, (I ſay, Reaſon, which is ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to all Laws, and therefore the Determiner of the Rectitude and Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of every Action, a thing confeſs'd every where;) let us ſtick to it; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we deſire to be inroll'd amongſt the number of thoſe who are delirious in one ſingle point, not by defectuous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, but from the untamed Carcer of their own Paſſions. For, whether ſome mens adheſion to others of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Principles, upon general Pretences of Love to mankind, or of an exploded Claim to Infallibility; or that other vain fears, which have diſorder'd their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings;
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:107015:69"/>or whether the deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and impolitick Expreſſions of ſome of our Clergy-men, as to their rather enduring the <hi>Roman,</hi> than the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Form</hi> (whereof there is no fear) be not a plain evidence, that ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are beſide themſelves, I leave wiſe men to determine.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall forbear the Gent. a little while, fearing to have tired the Reader's Patience, and being very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 'tis ſomething againſt the grain to plane with a Tool, whoſe edge is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready bazal'd, by his taking of it by the <hi>wrong handle,</hi> or not ſteady holding of it; or otherwiſe, poſſibly by his overwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning conceit of having the better Cauſe; but 'tis no great matter which way it come, nor which of us two are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, if ſome other better workman may chance to be awakend, or rowz'd up, to correct us both; which may be neceſſary, for ought I know; for, while two ſtrive, a third often gets the prize: this I am ſure of, men of general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation are the beſt Judges, not mere Book-men; the want of which, has, if
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:107015:70"/>not corrupted, yet apparently weakn'd the Judgment of a brave Perſon, and worthy the Title of a Learned, and very Rational men.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>M. Hale,</hi> that Vertuous and Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Judge, whoſe Law, as it is Piacular for me to queſtion, yet, if I ſhould with his <hi>Philoſophy</hi> unwritten, the wiſeſt would conclude me his Friend. This was that large capacious Head, who wanted the happineſs of Converſation; which, had he uſed, many Notions which he Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and thought rare, becauſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo to him in his Study, would have appeared very trite to himſelf; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, he had never, by their Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, taken off from the general opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion moſt men had of his Excellent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments Natural, and acquired Parts; <hi>but all — men have their blind ſides.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next ſhall be <hi>T. Hobs,</hi> whoſe Arguments no man ever condemn'd, who read him without Prejudice, and could underſtand them, and whoſe Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings plainly clear the difference betwixt a <hi>poring</hi> and a thinking man, which laſt he was, (pious in his Life, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:107015:70"/>like a true Chriſtian Philoſpher) yet, certainly, it had been impoſſible, (notwithſtanding his great Advantages of Learning, Quiet, long Life and Health) if he had not travell'd, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd with the greateſt Wits much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and at home in his younger time; for him to have made all men ſee, and his very Antagoniſts confeſs, the prodigious Strength of his Reaſon and Wit, whereof his golden Book <hi>de Cive,</hi> ſo valu'd by all Lawyers at home and abroad: (to ſpeak it for the Honour of <hi>England</hi>) and his Objections againſt Worthy <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> about his Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning the Queſtion, <hi>Whether we can have a proper Idaea of God, or not?</hi> are ſuch evident Proofs, that to deny it, is to be accounted ſtupid, or ſhort-ſighted: And for his Arguments about Liberty and Neceſſity, againſt Biſhop <hi>Bramhall,</hi> they are ſo hugely fine, and ſo curiouſly, yet naturally, cogent, that, for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 'twill be judg'd mere Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſuperadd any thing upon that Subject, ſo briskly canvaſs'd betwixt that Learned <hi>Prelate</hi> and him: and of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:107015:71"/>what great weight, and yet hardly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom'd conſequence, thoſe Arguments are, and how far the dilucidation of thoſe Points there handled, will operate in preſent and future Ages, the ſharpeſt Eyes now alive cannot penetrate; tho this inquiring time has ſhrewdly gueſs'd at it, and already improv'd thoſe undeniable Proofs to no ſmall Advantage, ev'n to the Expoſing of the School-men, and the old mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken Phyſicks, as waſte Paper, and Judicial Aſtrology to a Ridicule: Let the Reader conclude what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of <hi>all the ſtuff which is laid as a foundation to build upon by the two firſt, and may eaſily ſee beſides, the inconſiſtency of the third, if the Will be free.</hi> I am glad however, the Learned have left us the Faculty of Deliberation, and for ſuch men's poſitive impoſing, I take it to be for want of breeding.</p>
            <p>But, why ſhould our preſent great Pretenders to all the Wit and Learning, be troubled at our diffidence in their Judgments; when 'tis plain, Let them take out of Books (when they do find
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:107015:71"/>themſelves gall'd) never ſo imperiouſly, Private Preachers do every where, for Fortune, equalize the Pulpits, Quacks and old Women Phyſicians, and Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citors Lawyers: So hard a thing it is for Pedantick men, or for any others, who are too much affected with that pitiful Diſeaſe of keeping of themſelves in favour with themſelves (by refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to Books in Company) not to be tireſome, as well to their Oppoſers, as often to their beſt Friends: indeed ſuch Dogmatizers, who would <hi>brow-beat</hi> others, of better breeding, with ſuch endleſs Vanities, or a <hi>Spaniſh ſhrug,</hi> are the moſt incorrigible Fops about the Town; and had need, for all their Noiſe, and flatteries of their Friends, be cut of that Diſeaſe, which in <hi>Eſſex</hi> is call'd the <hi>Simples; but 'tis hard to find a fit Surgeon,</hi> where the wounded Party will not believe he is in danger; 'twere happy for ſuch men, if they had but juſt ſo much Wit, as to know themſelves to be half-witted: <hi>But the breed of theſe Teazers is Clerical, they are too eager, ſcud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and ranging.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:107015:72"/>
            <p>Nor is it leſs difficult to cure the itch of thoſe, who, on the one hand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to prove the <hi>grand</hi> ſinfulneſs of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and on the other hand, for the Alleviation of that Crime; whenas, at this time, to my knowledge, two parts of three of the moſt knowing Gentlemen, and others about <hi>London,</hi> are ſenſible, a man may be very ſafe without inclining to the one ſide or other; the whole Diſcourſe being about little, or, at beſt, indifferent Stuff; the Quarrel, I ſay, is about things of no great moment, if any at all, as to man's future happineſs.</p>
            <p>However, I would have thoſe eager ones for Conformity, well conſider the preſent <hi>Genius</hi> of the People occaſion'd by the late mutinous Times; whoſe tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and infuſions, as to Religion, are ſtill growing, and therefore render it wholly impracticable here to force a Conformity; unleſs 'twere poſſible to reduce <hi>England</hi> to that ſtate it was in before <hi>H. the Eighth</hi>'s time, <hi>when ſo great a part of the Land was in the Churches, and the Nobilities poſſeſſion; whereas now,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:107015:72"/>it is, in a great meaſure, come into the hands of Trading men, who ſet the meaner ſort at work,</hi> who are thereby oblig'd to be, or at leaſt ſeem to be, of their Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er's Opinion, who love Power, as all men do; and ſince, in other things, their Education, or other Incapacity bars them from the exerciſe thereof, they are pleas'd with ſuch homage as their Dependents do, and cannot avoid giving of them: and this tranſlation of Eſtates, if it have made the Church weaker, it <hi>has made the King ſtronger;</hi> for it has Enrich'd the Body of the Nation, in whoſe riches his Majeſties Strength conſiſts.</p>
            <p>And further (to ſpeak freely) I much queſtion, whether the <hi>Roman Religion</hi> could have hitherto been kept out, (at leaſt not ſo eaſily) if much of thoſe Lands, and other noble Eſtates ſince, had not been diſpers'd into Trading hands; and, as for the preſent proſpect of Affairs, where the one Party endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours (which is Natural) to introduce the Religion ſhut out by <hi>Laws,</hi> and the other Party (for it's now wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to whether <hi>Papiſt or Proteſtant</hi>)
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:107015:73"/>to keep their own in: I may conclude, 'tis <hi>London</hi> which ſtands in the way of the firſt, under his Majeſty, and is the Buckler for the Second; <hi>London,</hi> I ſay, the very Eye of the Three Nations, and Envy of the World, and will ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, if ſhe be ſo happy as to be ſenſible of her own Happineſs, and wherein it conſiſts; which is ſo obvious, that if any of her worthy Citizens be ignorant of it, they want that very thing I have ſo much magnify'd, and will confeſs it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better conſideration; when Time, or their own Experience ſhall furniſh 'em with a Glaſs to inſpect the Fidelity, and Diſcretion of their Friends, and the ill projects, and weak, ev'n of all thoſe alſo, who, upon what ſpecious colours ſoever, fall from the common Intereſt of this great City and Kingdom, into a diſcontented Humour, or dangerous Neutrality, which is worſe.</p>
            <p>But there is reaſon to hope, a ſhort time will produce ſuch ſerene Winds, from the Agreement of our Superiours, as will diſſipate thoſe dull Meteors which ſeem to threaten our Peace, tho, as the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:107015:73"/>Seas, after a Storm, will boyl a while, ſo it is impoſſible the Fears of the People, from the Provocations of ill men, ſhould vaniſh in an inſtant: but while the Groundſels are good, and the Studs ſound, there is no fear the Building will fall, tho it may rock to ſome degree. Let us patiently wait upon that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which never fails the juſt man, tho ſometims it ſeems to be unconcern'd in theſe Sublunary matters: but we are better inſtructed, and ſince we have liv'd to ſee the uſeleſneſs of all the old Philoſophy, which conſiſted merely in Words; of that kind of whifling The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology, which was compos'd, moſt what, of inſignificant Notions; and of that Phyſick, which, by its dull activity, was, for the moſt part, more tedious than the Diſeaſe; ſo we may hope, that Time, and the Exigency of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, will bring us into ſuch a freſh Compoſition, and new Fabrick of Laws, as ſhall chear up the hearts of all true <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants,</hi> and render his Sacred Majeſty more ſecure at home, and more formidable abroad; which, that it may
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:107015:74"/>be effected, is ſo reaſonable a Prayer, that I am confident all thoſe who but pretend to ſo Excellent a Ladies Favour as Reaſon is, and love their Native Soil, or enjoy the Repoſe of <hi>England,</hi> muſt cordially ſecond it; and will ſhew the Obduration of that ſort of men, whom, neither the long and proſperous Reign of that Queen, who baffl'd the, then <hi>greateſt Prince,</hi> and <hi>greateſt Biſhop,</hi> can yet convince, 'twas God's ſpecial Favour to a very good Cauſe; nor that the Preſervation of his Majeſties Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and the Body of the State, from that black Deſign, was beyond Humane Wit, and the mere Bleſſing of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power: nor that the Counſels of ſuch, who in the late unhappy Times produc'd ſuch deplorable Effects, were influenc'd by that very Society, which is not only — troubleſome now to us, as Proteſtants, but to the reſt of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> of milder tempers; theſe, I ſay, unconvinc'd of theſe Truths, I muſt leave to their own Weakneſs, for it can be no other; unleſs it be mere obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or ill Will, and they muſt thank
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:107015:74"/>themſelves, if thereby, they at laſt oblige our Government to a ſmarter Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Laws againſt them, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly; tho, I confeſs, 'tis the leſs wonder to me, that Perſons of inferiour degree among the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> ſhould grope in the dark, <hi>(who are the proper Subjects of the Kingdom of Darkneſs)</hi> ſince Day-light, from the preſent Miſts interpoſing at home, can hardly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; tho it may be pious to ſuppoſe, God may be pleas'd, even by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts, and alternate Diſputes of our own Clergy, to cancel all <hi>beggarly Rudiments</hi> of <hi>indifferent Forms,</hi> ſo much (too much) contended for, and perhaps, too eagerly oppos'd at this inſtant.</p>
            <p>Mean time, 'tis obſervable, what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate Enmity there has alwayes been betwixt thoſe, who claim their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Commiſſion to preach, from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and thoſe, who either do, or ſhould know, the Laws are their beſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; witneſs the Violence (and very fatal to our Peace) of the high Church-men before the Great Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt the old Puritan Miniſters,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:107015:75"/>then, the hard uſage of theſe laſt, when they got into the Power, towards the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Party, during the Civil Wars; &amp; the preſent eagerneſs of ſome to puniſh the Nonconforming Miniſters, <hi>which is not to do as we would be done unto:</hi> but the Jeſuits and Seculars do the ſame, ſuch is the general Diſeaſe of Eccleſiaſticks every where.</p>
            <p>The truth is, here is great clamour in ſome Pulpits, and otherwiſe, againſt the ſin of Separation, to prove it ſo (tho 'tis by others as briskly defended not to be a Sin) but how little is ſaid there againſt the publick Sins of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Many exclaim againſt Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but how few ſtand right as to the Publick Intereſt? as if the Laity were ſo blind, as not to obſerve theſe things, and that <hi>they that are not for truth are againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, It has been often known in <hi>England,</hi> and in our time, that Souldiers of different ſides, upon Renditions of Garriſons, Acts of Grace <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted Friendſhips, and lov'd one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afterwards; that Complainants
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:107015:75"/>and Defendants, after long and exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Chancery Suits, have agreed lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly, to a high degree of Friendſhip; that Tradeſ-men have lov'd and help'd one another, who have been Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, when there was room for both to live: that the greateſt <hi>Hectors</hi> and <hi>Huffs,</hi> after the Vapours of Wine were ſpent, have forgot their Quarrels, and hugg'd one another: Nay, our Women, who ſo ſeldome agree, (the fair ones) when Preferment has been open'd to each of two, have lov'd one another; but the Anger and Jealouſies of that other ſort of men, is unappeaſable, and will be ſo, while one ſide rubs old ſores too much, and the other ſide gives uncivil Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, ev'n to thoſe who have beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended the main Poſts againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> who alſo pretend to Reaſon, and take advantage by theſe interfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</p>
            <p>But what's the Reaſon of this Heat at home? Is it not for Power, and from Ambition? <hi>contrary to their Maſter's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> 'twere better if they would let theſe Diſputes alone, and, according to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:107015:76"/>their Duties, teach men Virtue, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſting in obedience to Laws; but theſe janglings will be endleſs, to the diſquiet of the People, while both ſides violate, by their Reflections, the <hi>Act of Grace,</hi> ſo ſolemnly penn'd, <hi>which retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to</hi> 1637, <hi>and extends to</hi> 1661.</p>
            <p>For my part, I know not why any wiſe man ſhould concern himſelf which ſide ſpeaks moſt to the purpoſe, <hi>(for 'tis all to me good purpoſe)</hi> ſince in other things about Religion, <hi>the more we know, the worſe they like us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 'tis well, we have at laſt found out, that Ignorance can never in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be the true Parent of either Civil or Theological Devotion: and 'tis plain, that unleſs the little, but notable Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deſcriber of the <hi>Roman</hi> Devices, (which out-does all the Theaters, how glorious ſoever ſince the Fire, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid Pulpits) if that Pen, I ſay, cannot be corrected, (which is true, as to matter of Fact) we ſhall yet infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely improve our Underſtandings; and if the Coffee-houſes, <hi>(thoſe open Enemies, and dangerous to the ſick Kingdom of Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries)</hi>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:107015:76"/>be not ſuppreſs'd, the ſolid truth of our Author's Aſſertion, which the Gent. carped at, but weakly, will ſhine ſtill brighter, <hi>viz. That it is impoſſible any man ſhould have been, is, or hereafter can be guided, by any other thing but his own Reaſon: as in all other things, ſo in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, I ſay,</hi> ſayes the Author, <hi>impoſſible: for in all Belief, and in all other Actions, the laſt Appeal is to Reaſon; for I believe this or that Doctrine, or do this or that action, becauſe I have ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it;</hi> and that this does juſtifie the whole Doctrine of his Treatiſe, and my Reply, is evident enough.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, this Apologetick Review and Appendix is written by me, who am one of thoſe very loth to be beſtridden by the Gallopers of either ſide: tho I ſhould rejoyce to ſee our Clergy love another, and the Diſſenting Miniſters al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to love the other; which can never be, whilſt the Paper skirmiſhing grows ranker and ranker; and, to ſpeak out, there can never be any cordial Affection, ev'n amongſt the Conforming Miniſters, while Preferments, and maintenance Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical are ſo unequally divided;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:107015:77"/>while ſo many worthy men can ſcarce get Bread, or muſt live too meanly; (for the Clergy-man of an indifferent Living is pinch't too much) and mean time, too many others abound with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Preferments; 'tis high time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form this Evil, and ſpecially now, when <hi>the Harveſt is great, &amp; the Labourers are too many,</hi> (or might be enough) if they were paid for their Work, which they are ready to do, or have done, and ought to be retain'd to do; while the Vermin are hov'ring about to devour and ſpoil the Crop by wide Mouths and ſharp Talons. But <hi>curſt Cows have ſhort Horns,</hi> and we begin neither to admire the Policies of that Party, nor have cauſe to value their Force, the firſt being fathomable by the eaſieſt capacity, and the ſecond prevented by the vigilancy of the Government.</p>
            <p>And, to my ſolid comfort, I well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the reſolution of my good Friend, Biſhop <hi>Gawden,</hi> while he was Parſon of <hi>Bocking,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> to my Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether, if I believ'd in God and Chriſt, I were obliged to be a Member of any particular Church or no; which was this; <hi>That if I were one of God's <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:107015:77"/>Church 'twas no great matter whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I were joyn'd to any petty Church Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon Earth, or no.</hi> A golden ſaying, and I muſt not belye the dead; and this Doctor kept his Parſonage all along till the Reſtauration of his Majeſty, and knew well, 'twas not neceſſary for him to be a Martyr of State in thoſe ugly convulſions of Government; tho he was ſo bravely honeſt, as, by an excellent and Loyal Proteſtation in Print, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade thoſe bad men, who then were about deſtroying of the King, and did do it, from ſo horrid a Crime; but when 'twas done, he ſat ſtill, and liv'd ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly, never oppoſing the Uſurpation to no purpoſe, as all wiſe men do, who wheel about when there is reaſon: And 'tis beſt to be ſilent, where Force (tho uſurped) runs high, and beyond the help of private men: and this made the Judges act in t'other times, for Right and Property muſt be maintain'd; and made Biſhop <hi>Juxon</hi> fall to hunting.</p>
            <p>And I never knew any man very wiſe, who ſhew'd himſelf eager to puniſh others for not complying with Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals about Religion; So the Peace be not
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:107015:78"/>violated, which is the greateſt of Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bleſſings, and which we have enjoy'd at home, ever ſince the King was reſtor'd, and whereof, I ſuppoſe, there will not in his time, (and long may he live) be any want, if this great Animal, <hi>the Empire of Great Britain,</hi> be but true to its own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to prove the truth of that Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime, let it be noted, how, for now above an hundred years experience, by the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of good men in <hi>Q. Maries</hi> days, and otherwiſe, it has been from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon, warranted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended againſt all the Wit and Machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the other ſide, ev'n to a plain baffle of late, by D. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> which deſerves all imaginable thankful reſpects.</p>
            <p>And let it be conſidered, that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is moſt conſonant to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the beſt, and moſt of his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, to our Common Laws, and our Form of Monarchy, and has been more than once ſignaliz'd with Bleſſings from Heaven, againſt all its dangerous Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents.</p>
            <p>This, I ſay, is the prop of our Peace, and the proper Antidote againſt Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:107015:78"/>Atheiſm and Popery (which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable) when it is ſecur'd by wholſom Laws, and their due Execution (the Life of all Laws) unto which Sanctions, all <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> from their Protection under them, are oblig'd, by the Laws of Reaſon, to render obedience; at leaſt, they ſhould not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to pervert others from it.</p>
            <p>Whence this concluſion naturally ariſes, That the Diſturbers of our Peace at this time in <hi>England,</hi> of what ſort ſoever (ſo protected) are unreaſonable men, where there is ſuch plenty, and where, all Arts and Sciences flouriſh to a degree beyond any part of the habitable World; and thence it follows, that if any ingenious Perſon is uneaſie here, he ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if his want of Humility, ſeverity of Opinion upon begg'd Principles, Creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or too great an eſteem of his own Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, have not made him ſo uneaſie.</p>
            <p>But further, If neither the ſearching Wits of the <hi>Rainbow</hi> Coffee-houſe, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Learning of <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Gown-men at <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Croſs,</hi> the fixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mercury of <hi>Fuller's Rents,</hi> the <hi>Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions</hi> of <hi>Charing Croſs,</hi> nor the <hi>huge ſtrength of the new Chappel near the great Arch,</hi> can
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:107015:79"/>reduce us to Moderation, nor ſatisfie our Doubts and Fears: if the Ludicrous Drolls of future Fortune cannot be foreſeen by the higheſt Star-gazing Philoſophers; no nor by the Magick of honeſt <hi>Fl.</hi> If the quainteſt Lawyers cannot agree, whether a Pardon, after an Impeachment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Publick hand, ſignifie ſomething or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; If ſome rank high Eccleſiaſticks cannot be cur'd of their Melancholy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vent'ring to take that <hi>Ignatian Powder,</hi> which will never do their Buſineſs, and does but ſuſpend the Fever: Nevertheleſs, let the Winds ſhift as they may, the Lee Port is at hand, and ſafe, <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> which will ſhelter us from ſtorms, if men, in their ſtations, will diſcreetly follow its guidance, <hi>as the ſafeſt Rule for Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; for the examination of all Doctrines obtruded by Humane Authority, and of every miraculous pretenſion, as the beſt meaſure of Conſcience (becauſe of Scripture;)</hi> without whoſe free Uſe, (I mean of Reaſons,) Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence will paſs for Senſe, Stupidity for Diſcretion, Fury for Valour, the Town <hi>Bullies and Cullies</hi> for the moſt accompliſht Gentlemen, hagg'd Curtezans for modeſt Ladies, and the moſt ſenſleſs, infatuated
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:107015:79"/>
               <hi>Bigots</hi> for the moſt Religious: therefore, to avoid miſtakes of ſuch natures, or at leaſt, to allay the ſharpneſs of our Epidemical Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>I hope I have, in this Reply, and by the favour of Reaſon, not only defeated the Forlorn, but the united <hi>Phalanx</hi> of the Gentleman's beſt diſciplin'd Infantry, and his Body of Horſe alſo, who durſt oppoſe Reaſon's Bravery and Strength.</p>
            <p>It remains, that I come off as civilly with him, as he does with the Author, where at laſt he ſays, that he (the Author) could not be angry with him upon his own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: for, ſays the <hi>Gent.</hi> I have guided my ſelf in my Anſwer wholly by my own Reaſon, which I thank him for, he having thereby juſtifi'd the whole Treatiſe of the Author's, and thereby ſhrivl'd his Anſwer into waſte Paper; and ſerves to ſhew, that my Replying is no greater Crime than his was, who was charged to ſay, <hi>O. Cromwel's</hi> Horſe was ſhod with Iron; and far ſhort of <hi>Banks</hi> his ſin, who ſhod his with Gold; tho the one eſcapt the High Court of Juſtice, yet the other could not the Star Chamber; the Uſurpt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the firſt diſſolving naturally,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:107015:80"/>for defect of eſſential Rights to ſuſtain it; and the ſecond being aboliſht for Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy; which Defect can never juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Diſobedience to Lawful Sovereignty, as ours is; and whereunto, if <hi>Calvin</hi>'s <hi>Caſe</hi> had ne're been printed, I ſhould have rationally ſubmitted, becauſe my obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lyes in the nature of my Submiſſion; Oaths adding nothing to it; and our Laws ſay, Obedience is due from Nature; wherein, Sir <hi>R. F.</hi> my Countrey man is right, tho out in other things; and tho <hi>Paul</hi> adviſes Obedience, not for Fear, but Conſcience, yet is an equivocal word, never us'd in the Old Teſtament, and more ſubject to Errour than Reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe leſs ſupported by ſolid Argument, and too often dazl'd by Enthuſiaſm, the Diſeaſe of Reaſon, and Conſcience alſo, which firſt, to ſpeak humanely, muſt yet be admitted to be the elder, conſidering God's <hi>Inhibition probational to Adam,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But, to let that Myſtery alone, and yet to leave nothing unweigh'd, which the Gent. has offer'd againſt Humane Reaſon; Upon Review of his Anſwer, I am oblig'd to ſay once more, that one part of three in it ſwells with illogical Conſequences,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:107015:80"/>and is againſt conſtant Experience: for he undertakes to ſhew what miſchiefs muſt come to paſs, if Liberty of Conſcience were permitted: as to that, 'tis plainly otherwiſe; for, ſince Liberty has been ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally aſſum'd, the Nation has been very peaceable and obedient every way other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; this, I ſay, is another experimental confutation of the main part of his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I would not have the <hi>Gent.</hi> ſpoil the Tone of his Stomach by Choler, if I do diſcomply with him in not grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the not ſo horrible conſequences of ſuch a Liberty, as he preſumes, contrary to Reaſon and Experience: For if the <hi>Gent</hi>'s. deſire had been ſeconded with Execution rigorouſly againſt the Diſſenters, it might have hazarded the putting of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation into great Diſorder by this time: his words being, <hi>Pag.</hi> 152 <hi>of Plain Deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That if the Nobility and Gentry will not ſuppreſs the Sectaries, by the Execution of the Laws, they will ſoon arrive at that height, that the Sword muſt do it, or elſe there will be no Government at all in our Nation:</hi> but what if it be impracticable to ſuppreſs them, becauſe the People will not accuſe one another?</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:107015:81"/>
            <p>'Tis true, Reaſon of State has been forc'd to ſtrike ſmartly that other ſort of men, who, by their barbarous and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Actions, have dared to confront the Government, but I hope they will be made wiſer hereafter, by the late Examples of publick and infamous Inflictions; <hi>for, it ſeems, the Common Law is in many Caſes in the breaſts of the Judges, de Modo Poenae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let the Event be what it will, (to uſe the <hi>Gent</hi>'s. own words, in the cloſe of his Anſwer) I muſt alſo with him profeſs, that I have fully ſatisfi'd not only my <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> but my <hi>Reaſon</hi> alſo, <hi>which is the ſurer way, and from better motives,</hi> in this Reply, by ſhewing my ſelf, according to my Duty, a ſincere Lover of Peace, of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in general, and of that particular Religion, the ſupport whereof I have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted to be the true Intereſt of <hi>England,</hi> and was alwayes ſo eſteem'd ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p>And I will add my promiſe to the Gent. and that upon the word of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>(which ought to be as ſacred as that of a Prieſt)</hi> that if he ſhall pleaſe to give me a Rejoynder <hi>without departure from his
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:107015:81"/>firſt Plea,</hi> I will not demurr for want of Form, but leave the Diſpute to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of indifferent Judges, upon the whole Argument, <hi>viz. Whether Humane Reaſon be not the beſt and ſafeſt Guide, with its due helps, beyond Popes, Councils, Fathers, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and all Books whatſoever, the Scripture excepted;</hi> which yet, if any man will ask me how I think to underſtand, I can give him no other Anſwer but this, that I muſt do it by Reaſon, which is the only Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent God has indu'd me with, for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation here, and hereafter; and <hi>by which, and no other mediation, it's poſſible, for a man of good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and not clogg'd with falſe Principles, to be ſatisfy'd, that the natural Dictates of God (Reaſon) carry no repugnancy to the Law and Will of God, revealed in the Scripture; the ſtudy of which Learning, is the foundation of all true Ratiocination, and the moſt generous, and moſt uſeful Science for all men to aſpire unto, who would know their reſpective Duties, as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Subjects;</hi> and upon the Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which Axiome, it is, that our Law of <hi>England,</hi> (if it were well digeſted into Method, certainly the beſt in the World)
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:107015:82"/>does ſay, that if any Law ſhall be enacted contrary to Reaſon, it is void, <hi>eo inſtante;</hi> becauſe contrary to God's undoubted E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Law, the Law of Reaſon, my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince to maintain: wherein, if any thing have ſlipt from my Pen, not conſiſtent with the Duty of a good Subject, or true Chriſtian, I do, ſubmiſſively and heartily beg pardon for it.</p>
            <p>And, to compleat my candid, and, at preſent, ſole Deſign of ſupporting Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon's Energy, and for the juſtification of <hi>H.</hi> the Eighth's forſaking the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and thereby to juſtifie the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Proteſtant Religion: let the Reader conſult the Decretory Council held under, and by the Command of Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, 1538, Printed 1609 at <hi>London,</hi> and taken out of Mr. <hi>Craſhaw</hi>'s Library, then Preacher of the Temple, wherein the Abuſes of the <hi>Roman</hi> Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks are manifeſted, under the Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate of Nine of the moſt Eminent Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals then living, (whereof <hi>Pool</hi> was one, and <hi>Sadolete</hi> another) to whoſe Inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Inquiry was then referr'd by the ſaid Pope; which Abuſes, the Court of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:107015:82"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> would not then correct, nor are they yet corrected, the Book being ſuppreſs'd by Order of that Church, and coming to my hands ſomething late from a worthy Bencher of <hi>Grayes Inn,</hi> which, otherwiſe, had ſooner been made Uſe of, to prove Reaſon a ſafer Guide than that Church which pretends to Infallibility, and may ſerve for Anſwer to that <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> who publiſhed ſome weak Reflections upon our Author's Diſcourſe of <hi>Humane Reaſon,</hi> who, if he fail'd in any thing handled in his Book, 'twas in his a little too ſlightly referring the Cauſe of <hi>H.</hi> the Eighth's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of the <hi>Roman</hi> See to his Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp;c. For, that there were many other concurring motives to his Deſertion, is very probable, from ſome Speeches I have ſeen of his in Parliament, and from Hiſtories about him, who was, tho a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, yet withal, a very ſtout and inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Prince, and fitted thereby for the Work he ſo worthily began, and whereof the Advantage accrues to us at this time: Such are the unſearchable depths of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which, tho few obſerve, and fewer are willing to reſign their Wills unto, will do what is beſt for good men.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:107015:83"/>
            <p>Laſtly, Becauſe ſome men are moſt gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Book Authorities, I think fit to add, that <hi>Montaigne, Eraſmus, Raymond Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond, Charone, Caſſauder, Chillingworth, Carte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Milton, Gell, Baxter,</hi> and <hi>Hobbs</hi> alſo, with others of Fame, as D. <hi>Stillingfleet,</hi> not to forget Biſhop <hi>Tayler,</hi> have unanimouſly approv'd of Reaſon as the beſt Guide, and favour'd, or cooly advis'd, a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd Toleration, I having named <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> before: but I refer the ingenuous Reader, once for all, to that excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>of the Riſe and Power of Parliaments, Laws, Courts, &amp;c. and of Religion,</hi> printed 1677. by way of Letter to a Parliament-man, wherein, a Toleration in Religion here, for all (but the Jeſuits and Seculars) is argued to be, not onely Political, but high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rational, and conſonant to the Doctrine of the Holy Jeſus; of which Opinion, till I am convinc'd otherwiſe by Reaſon, I am reſolv'd to be, and no longer, for I cannot.</p>
            <p>Mean time, as a Corollary to this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, I ſubjoyn, with ſubmiſſion, that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears plainly, by his Majeſties Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Golden Book, he was not much averrſe to it; and that ev'n <hi>Charles</hi> the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:107015:83"/>Fifth, during the <hi>Interim,</hi> (ſee <hi>Sleydan</hi>) did allow a kind of Toleration in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> where I leave the Cauſe, but really unwillingly; for, further Proofs crowd ſo faſt into me, that to forbear venting them, is a kind of Diſeaſe upon me, tho, I hope, not Mortal. Neither do I ſtand in awe of any Cenſure upon my Concluſions, alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy publiſh'd, by the future Impreſſions of any Bigotical Opponent whatſoever.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Epitaphium <hi>Cliffordianum.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>HIC jacet inſignis</hi> Cliffordi <hi>capſula, terrae</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reddita, ſed melior pars reſoluta Polo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Carmine non opus eſt famam celebrare, polite</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(Ni fallor) Libro gloria certa micat.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Humanae Rationis <hi>opus munivit, &amp; ultro</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eſſe ducem vitae, ſubſidiumque viae.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si quae praeterea ſuperaddere vota Poe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auderet, nitida ſacrificanda manu.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Engliſhed.</head>
               <l>HEre, ſnatcht by Death, <hi>Clifford</hi> interr'd does lye,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Nobler Part is vehicl'd on high;</l>
               <l>There needs no Muſe to celebrate his Fame,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Book eterniz'd has his gen'rous Name.</l>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:107015:84"/>
               <l>He proved <hi>Humane Reaſon's</hi> worth ſo well,</l>
               <l>From other Arts it bears away the Bell.</l>
               <l>If any Poet ſuperadds to this,</l>
               <l>With impure hands, his <hi>Holocauſt</hi>'s amiſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His Character.</head>
               <p>AS to his Perſon, 'twas little, his Face rather flat than oval, his Eye ſerious, Countenance Leonine, his Conſtitution Cholerick, Sanguine, tinctur'd with Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly: of a facetious Converſation; yet a great Humoriſt; of quick Parts, ſo of quick Paſſions, and Venereal, thence Lazy; he was learned, very critical, poſitive and proud, charitable enough, and ſcorn'd to be rich; he had a will to be juſt; would drink to exceſs ſometimes. His Religion was that of his Countrey; he was always Loyal to his King, and a very good Poet. He died 'twixt 50 and 60, at <hi>Sutton</hi>'s <hi>Hoſpital,</hi> whoſe Maſter he then was; not much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the Penſioners; few knew him well. He was a man ſtrangely compos'd; 'tis queſtion'd whether his Virtues or Vices were moſt; I incline to the laſt, yet he departed peaceably and piouſly.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:107015:84"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
